<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?rfc notedraftinprogress=""?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle=""?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" docName="draft-kowalik-domainconnect-03" category="std" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en" version="3" >
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Domain Connect">Domain Connect Protocol - DNS provisioning between Services and DNS Providers</title>
    <seriesInfo value="draft-kowalik-domainconnect-03" status="Informational" stream="IETF" name="Internet-Draft" asciiName="Internet-Draft"></seriesInfo>
    <seriesInfo name="" value="" status="standard"></seriesInfo>
    <author initials="P" surname="Kowalik">
      <organization>DENIC eG</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street ascii="Theodor-Stern-Kai 1">Theodor-Stern-Kai 1</street>
          <city ascii="Frankfurt am Main">Frankfurt am Main</city>
          <country ascii="DE">DE</country>
        </postal>
        <email>pawel.kowalik@denic.de</email>
        <uri>https://denic.de</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="A" surname="Blinn">
      <address>
        <postal></postal>
        <email>arnold@arnoldblinn.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="J" surname="Kolker">
      <organization>GoDaddy Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street ascii="14455 N. Hayden Rd. #219">14455 N. Hayden Rd. #219</street>
          <city ascii="Scottsdale">Scottsdale</city>
          <country ascii="US">US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>jkolker@godaddy.com</email>
        <uri>https://www.godaddy.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="S" surname="Kerola">
      <organization>Cloudflare, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street ascii="101 Townsend St">101 Townsend St</street>
          <city ascii="San Francisco">San Francisco</city>
          <country ascii="US">US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>kerolasa@cloudflare.com</email>
        <uri>https://cloudflare.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date day="2" year="2025" month="September"></date>
    <area>Applications and Real-Time</area>
    <abstract>

<t anchor="_1a4ffd2e-21ad-66d5-35fe-8917664ac67c">This document provides specification of the Domain Connect Protocol that was built to support DNS configuration provisioning between Service Providers (hosting, social, email, hardware, etc.) and DNS Providers.</t>
</abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="_3659af9f-d04c-e5a1-88c6-e474cd445df3"><name>Acknowledgements</name>

<t anchor="_c0f72b94-0cd9-a9c5-fe87-3473b8ef62e8">The authors wish to thank the following persons for their feedback and suggestions as well as for the previous work on the standard:</t>

<ul anchor="_498f38e0-712f-0857-412e-8bfbd60a471a"><li>Roger Carney of GoDaddy Inc.</li>
<li>Chris Ambler of GoDaddy Inc.</li>
<li>Darrel Miller</li>
<li>Peter Thomassen</li>
<li>Paul Hoffmann</li>
<li>Arnt Gulbrandsen</li>
</ul>
</section>
    <section anchor="_c262b60c-e515-282f-314a-924c08799608"><name>Introduction</name>

<t anchor="_3ffbb0fb-0027-4919-9094-f560d5b0c8c6">Connecting a domain name to a service should be a simple and straightforward process.  However, historically, users have faced a complex and often frustrating task involving manual DNS configuration.  Traditional methods are unreliable, require deep technical knowledge of DNS, and result in outdated and confusing instructions from Service Providers.  This leads to user frustration, support overhead, and abandoned setups.</t>

<t anchor="_8cf97ac4-95d4-4f27-adad-e79d76118643">To address these challenges, Domain Connect offers a streamlined and automated solution.  It empowers Service Providers to easily enable their services to work with user domains, simplifying both DNS provider discovery and DNS configuration.  By abstracting away the complexities of manual DNS management through user-friendly web interactions, standard authentication, and template-based configurations, Domain Connect significantly improves the user experience.</t>
</section>
    <section anchor="_eefabcb7-75d8-aa34-d07a-674d827214f6"><name>Use Cases</name>

<section anchor="_f1e61f16-04d0-8933-354e-3663f2e686fb"><name>Primary Use Cases</name>

<t anchor="_574252b8-12b1-eb99-3472-c66ffcdc4696">The following use cases illustrate the wide range of applications where Domain Connect simplifies and automates DNS configuration, from basic service onboarding to complex, dynamic DNS management scenarios.</t>

<ul anchor="_06b1cc58-f7bf-3d0c-0e64-a6de3b09c450"><li><strong>SaaS Provider with One-Off DNS Configuration:</strong> A Software as a Service (SaaS) Provider offering functionality with an option to assign own domain name, such as web hosting or email, can utilize Domain Connect to streamline the process of configuring DNS records for their customers. This automation eliminates the need for manual configuration and simplifies the onboarding experience for users.</li>
<li><strong>SaaS Provider with Multi-Step DNS Configuration:</strong> Some SaaS Providers may require a multi-step DNS configuration process, potentially involving asynchronous operations. For example, a service might require initial verification of domain ownership through a TXT record, followed by the creation of CNAME records for different subdomains. Domain Connect can handle such scenarios by utilizing its asynchronous flow. This allows the Service Provider to obtain user consent and apply the necessary DNS changes in multiple steps, even if the user is not actively present during the entire process.</li>
<li><strong>On-Premise Service with Publicly Accessible DNS Service:</strong> An on-premise service, such as a local network device or server, can also benefit from Domain Connect if it utilizes a publicly accessible DNS service. By leveraging Domain Connect, the service can automatically update DNS records as needed, ensuring that the service remains accessible through its domain name.</li>
<li><strong>Tool or Service with Regularly Updated DNS Entries:</strong> A tool or service that requires regular updates to DNS entries, such as a dynamic DNS service or a DNS-based load balancer, can use Domain Connect to automate the process.</li>
<li><strong>Packaged Software Provider:</strong> A packaged software provider, whether open-source or proprietary, can integrate Domain Connect into their installation and configuration process. This allows the software to automatically configure necessary DNS records during installation, simplifying the setup process for users. However, if the software is installed on a private network with a private DNS service, it might not be directly compatible with Domain Connect, unless the DNS service provides Domain Connect endpoints accessible to the installation process.</li>
</ul>
</section>

<section anchor="_325990a0-cd0c-1e35-eaf8-82d7438a43b9"><name>Use Cases out of scope</name>

<t anchor="_9beb328e-19ff-dd26-7949-3bc1511d7bc6">While Domain Connect offers significant advantages in automating DNS configuration, it's important to recognize scenarios where it might not be the ideal solution:</t>

<ul anchor="_307670b5-6db3-5a04-00db-fef7854f0932"><li><strong>Automation or CI/CD Pipelines:</strong> Domain Connect is primarily designed for user-driven DNS configuration, where an end user grants consent and applies changes. Automating this process within CI/CD pipelines or other automated workflows can be challenging, as it requires obtaining and securely storing OAuth tokens beforehand. However, if authorisation tokens are pre-obtained from a user-driven setup process, Domain Connect can be also integrated into automation workflows.</li>
<li><strong>Private/Enterprise DNS with Public SaaS Providers:</strong> Domain Connect relies on public DNS records and endpoints to facilitate discovery and configuration. If a private or enterprise DNS service is used, it might not be directly compatible with Domain Connect, unless the DNS service provides publicly accessible Domain Connect endpoints.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
    <section anchor="_3fd8bb92-822a-fcb0-725e-99a90e67edf4" toc="exclude"><name>Terminology</name>

<t anchor="_7d106f2e-b997-be15-8b5d-40e0b35b64de">The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119" section="" relative=""></xref> <xref target="RFC8174" section="" relative=""></xref> when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>

<t anchor="_63f3f500-10eb-cbdd-8218-42f7d7278094">The Terms like "<strong>Registrar</strong>", "<strong>Authoritative server</strong>", "<strong>Zone</strong>", "<strong>Zone Apex</strong>" or "<strong>Sub Domain</strong>" are used as defined in <xref target="RFC8499" section="" relative=""></xref>.</t>

<t anchor="_90f1b70c-45e9-03da-8244-ac206127d20d">This specification uses the Augmented Backus-Naur Form (ABNF) notation of <xref target="RFC5234" section="" relative=""></xref>. The following ABNF rules are imported from the normative references <xref target="RFC5234" section="" relative=""></xref>.</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_e571ef13-0ac2-f9ff-71ff-f50eeaacd84c" type="abnf"><![CDATA[     ALPHA          =  %x41-5A / %x61-7A   ; A-Z / a-z
     DIGIT          =  %x30-39             ; 0-9]]></sourcecode>


<dl anchor="_f723e3f0-780f-a26c-c9cc-c0656e6484fe"><dt>Service Provider:</dt><dd anchor="_9083d0f6-63af-d9da-bd61-aff2290c0892"><t anchor="_824a3fc5-1608-a6c3-d7f7-6791acec7268">An entity that offers products and services that are configured or accessed using domain names. These services typically rely on DNS for setup, discovery and/or operation. Examples include web hosting, email services, cloud platforms, and other online applications.</t>
</dd><dt>DNS Provider:</dt><dd anchor="_a1a36f81-5e63-0ea6-bbce-5949292743fa"><t anchor="_826462fd-0c86-b560-4a32-4384ad004cec">An entity that offers DNS zone hosting services. DNS Providers are responsible for hosting the DNS zone for a domain name and providing the necessary tools to manage the DNS records. DNS Provider would be an Authoritative server operator for the hosted zones, or would have a contractual relationship with the operator to manage zone distribution over DNS.</t>
</dd><dt>User:</dt><dd anchor="_0d8e6325-9843-f131-169c-b4b54de57257"><t anchor="_b6eb0026-4636-34e8-616b-8d7e775db481">Refers to the end-user who has means to control domain name's DNS configuration at DNS Provider and wishes to configure it to work with a service provided by a Service Provider.</t>
</dd><dt>Service Template/Template:</dt><dd anchor="_ea6da2fd-de8b-214d-bbfe-1ad87dd1d4a8"><t anchor="_b4d684d6-add3-7aac-674a-202033f65942">A structured data format that describes a set of configurations for DNS records required by a Service Provider to configure a certain service together with metadata related to the control flow of Domain Connect protocol. A template is used as a mean of communication between Service Provider and DNS Provider.</t>
</dd><dt>Public Template Repository:</dt><dd anchor="_527d9b09-93ea-3323-4a08-ee4c7e70f99e"><t anchor="_00ccb837-5bd4-cb30-d8e4-2da295f14611">A publicly accessible repository of Service Templates, formatted in a standardized manner, intended to facilitate sharing, discovery, and reuse of service configurations. (Read more: <xref target="repository-and-integrity"></xref>).</t>
</dd></dl>
</section>
    <section anchor="_98fc7268-f41c-0906-5351-d97b9c7a67de"><name>Protocol design</name>

<section anchor="_5cb96e73-a546-b572-74cc-239df13af194"><name>Templates</name>

<t anchor="_01ed9779-ed57-051a-ce6d-a1217fdd612b">Templates are core to Domain Connect, as they fully describe a service owned by a Service Provider and contain all of the information necessary to enable and operate/maintain the service in the form of a set of records.</t>

<t anchor="_9b86bcf8-274d-1fa5-2b02-7127b332f386">The individual records in a template MAY be assigned to a group identified by a groupId. This allows for the application of templates in different stages. For example, an email provider might first set a TXT record to verify the domain, and later set an MX record to configure email delivery. While done separately, both changes are fundamentally part of the same service.</t>

<t anchor="_3c0460cd-a8c1-8085-0d3b-3177b2fee7b7">Templates MAY also contain variable portions, as often values of data in DNS change based on the implementation and/or user of the service (e.g. the IP address of a service, a user id, etc.).</t>

<t anchor="_fc81b17e-6fb5-445b-acc1-aafbcd9a6149">The template is defined by the Service Provider and manually onboarded with the DNS Provider, according to a template definition published in the <xref target="repository-and-integrity">Public Repository</xref> or agreed out-of-band between the Service Provider and the DNS Provider.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="_1b56a3dd-c3b3-cb25-4530-cafb656a8450"><name>Trust Model</name>

<t anchor="_2b545bff-b308-a3eb-fb82-da1eea3a7efc">The Domain Connect protocol relies on a robust trust model to ensure the security and reliability of DNS configuration delegation between Service Providers and DNS Providers.  This model addresses the necessary trust relationships between users, Service Providers, and DNS Providers, centering on secure template utilization and DNS Provider vetting processes.</t>

<section anchor="_c93061f6-7a18-8245-9aa4-e04ecc6a7e16"><name>Trust Establishment</name>

<t anchor="_7a11069d-0afb-1b38-32f7-ae61bef9e425">User trust in the DNS Provider is an essential factor. DNS Provider is a trusted party by the fact that DNS Provider has full technical access to the DNS zone already. Users depend on their DNS Providers to accurately reflect DNS record modifications initiated through Domain Connect. Consequently, DNS Providers are expected implement authorization checks to validate user permissions prior to enacting any DNS zone changes. Furthermore, DNS Providers are responsible for translating template specifications into a human-readable format, enabling users to readily comprehend the nature and impact of proposed DNS record changes.</t>

<t anchor="_3e7d69a0-d5ab-1f12-ce38-2a8f92e08cc9">Users would typically place trust in Service Providers to act responsibly and only make DNS modifications that are within the scope defined by the approved template, however it shall be observed that a malicious actor may try to exploit this trust by acting as a benign Service Provider or building a fake one, therefore by default Service Provider shall not be assumed to be a trusted party in the protocol considerations.</t>

<t anchor="_1deae246-a8ae-5ebb-c370-d5329a5d8f90">A foundational element to close this gap is the establishment of trust between DNS Providers and Service Providers. DNS Providers verify the legitimacy and security of templates provided by Service Providers as well as they are able to verify textual information included in the template and provided to the user, such as provider name or service name. This trust is typically established through an onboarding process which may involve contractual agreements or appropriate template acceptance policies.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="_3c43119a-e32e-4807-e0c4-22310db14626"><name>Template Security</name>

<t anchor="_bf49c8a7-0b9e-b761-de51-1d65b55e77cd">Templates are central to the trust model, defining the permitted scope of DNS zone modifications and restricting Service Provider actions, preventing unauthorized changes beyond the template's specified parameters. The template defines the types of DNS records within the zone and together with a distinct domain name and optionally sub-domain with user consent it defines clearly the part of the zone that the Service Provider is authorized to modify via the template application. Service Providers create templates which are then onboarded by DNS Providers, either adhering to a published template definition or based on bilateral agreements. The DNS Provider has very explicit knowledge and control of the settings being changed to enable a service.</t>
</section>
</section>
</section>
    <section anchor="_564ffc29-8d3d-ab36-2073-bf2b3dca8bb0"><name>Protocol Flows</name>

<section anchor="_84c8465e-c69f-f068-5c2b-cc530266de83"><name>General information</name>

<t anchor="_192579e0-1896-a551-1984-1e0c1e20e7e1">To attach a domain name to a service provided by a Service Provider, the user would first enter their domain name.</t>

<t anchor="_ccda0464-67af-f06c-7621-7467c239f758">Instead of relying on examination of the nameservers and mapping these to DNS Providers, DNS Provider discovery is handled through simple records in DNS and an API. The Service Provider queries for a specific record in the zone that returns a REST endpoint to initiate the protocol. When this endpoint is called, a Domain Connect compliant DNS Provider returns information about that domain and how to configure it using Domain Connect.</t>

<t anchor="_567dbccb-401e-56ce-16ee-d7005d48fbb3">To apply the changes to DNS, there are two use cases. The first is a synchronous web flow, and the second is an asynchronous flow using OAuth and an API.</t>

<t anchor="_33b6321e-36c1-9f5c-a583-c1deb2e0ee73">It is noted that a DNS Provider MAY choose to only implement one of the flows, however it is RECOMMENDED to implement Synchronous Flow which fulfill needs of most Service Providers.</t>

<t anchor="_a307aa69-29c5-ad2a-95da-7fd90c152b2d">Individual Service Providers MAY work with the synchronous flow only, the asynchronous flow only, or with both.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="_0fb4c7b6-a0ca-2357-b89f-3699cedeed8b"><name>The Synchronous Flow</name>

<t anchor="_a8690e14-af34-ddf6-ba5c-8c8e9a8db2e6">This flow is tailored for the Service Provider that requires a one time synchronous change to DNS.</t>

<figure anchor="_f17f079c-6439-a2ba-879e-5ffab828d667">

<name>Sequence diagram of Synchronous Flow</name><artwork type="ascii-art"><![CDATA[       ,-.
       `-'
       /|\
        |     ,----------------.   ,------------.          ,----------.
       / \    |Service Provider|   |DNS Provider|          |DNS Server|
      User    `--------+-------'   `------+-----'          `-----+----'
     1 Provides domain name               |                      |
        |------------->|                  |                      |
        |              |                  |                      |
        |              |       2 Initiates DNS discovery         |
        |              |---------------------------------------->|
        |              |                  |                      |
        |              |         3 Responds with                 |
        |              |         discovery URL fragment          |
        |              |<----------------------------------------|
        |              |                  |                      |
        |        4 Requests DNS Provider settings                |
        |              |----------------->|                      |
        |              |                  |                      |
        |              5 Provides settings|                      |
        |              |<-----------------|                      |
        |              |                  |                      |
        |        6 Queries for supported template                |
        |              |----------------->|                      |
        |              |                  |                      |
        |              7 Responds template|                      |
        |              support status     |                      |
        |              |<-----------------|                      |
        |              |                  |                      |
   8 Presents connection link             |                      |
        |<-------------|                  |                      |
        |              |                  |                      |
        |  9 Navigates to DNS Provider    |                      |
        |-------------------------------->|                      |
        |              |                  |                      |
        |              |                  |                      |
        _________________________________________________________|
        ! ALT  /  if the template requires signing               !
        !_____/        |                  |                      !
        !              10 Lookup URL      |                      !
        !              signature keys (DNS)                      !
        !              |<-----------------|                      !
        !              |                  |                      !
        !              |                  |----.                 !
        !              |                  |    | 11 Check        !
        !              |                  |<---' request URL     !
        !              |                  |      signature       !
        !              |                  |                      !
        !~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~!
        |              |                  |                      |
        |   12 Requests authentication    |                      |
        |<--------------------------------|                      |
        |              |                  |                      |
        |        13 Authenticate          |                      |
        |-------------------------------->|                      |
        |              |                  |                      |
        |              |                  |----.                 |
        |              |                  |    | 14 Check domain |
        |              |                  |<---' ame in          |
        |              |                  |      customer's      |
        |              |                  |      account         |
        |              |                  |                      |
        |              |                  |                      |
        15 Requests consent for DNS changes                      |
        |<--------------------------------|                      |
        |              |                  |                      |
        |      16 Confirms consent        |                      |
        |-------------------------------->|                      |
        |              |                  |                      |
        |              |                  17 Apply changes to DNS|
        |              |                  |--------------------->|
        |              |                  |                      |
        |           18 Redirect/ Close window                    |
        |              |<- - - - - - - - -|                      |
        |              |                  |                      |
        |              |          19 Query DNS records           |
        |              |---------------------------------------->|
        |              |                  |                      |
        |              |           20 New DNS records            |
        |              |<----------------------------------------|
        |              |                  |                      |
       21 Report success                  |                      |
        |<-------------|                  |                      |]]></artwork></figure>

<t anchor="_913075b2-a7ff-43a3-28c7-84fdbb6f8fd8">Steps:</t>

<ol anchor="_33bcd8ca-ad52-0b3f-c5aa-76235bb78872" type="1"><li><strong>User Provides Domain Name</strong>: The user initiates the process by providing their domain name to the Service Provider.</li>
<li><strong>Service Provider Initiates DNS Discovery</strong>: The Service Provider queries the DNS provider to discover the Domain Connect settings for the given domain.</li>
<li><strong>DNS Provider Responds with Discovery URL Fragment</strong>: The DNS Provider responds with a URL fragment containing information where to query settings of DNS provider for a domain name.</li>
<li><strong>Service Provider Requests DNS Provider Settings</strong>: The Service Provider uses the URL fragment to request the complete Domain Connect settings from the DNS Provider.</li>
<li><strong>DNS Provider Provides Settings</strong>: The DNS Provider provides the settings, including information about API endpoints.</li>
<li><strong>Service Provider Queries for Supported Template</strong>: The Service Provider checks if the DNS Provider supports the specific template required for the service.</li>
<li><strong>DNS Provider Responds with Template Support Status</strong>: The DNS Provider confirms if they support the requested template.</li>
<li><strong>Service Provider Presents Connection Link</strong>: The Service Provider presents a connection link to the user, which leads to the DNS Provider's Domain Connect service.</li>
<li><strong>User Navigates to DNS Provider</strong>: The user navigates the link and user agent is directed to the DNS Provider's website.</li>
<li><strong>DNS Provider Performs URL Lookup and Signature Key Verification (if required)</strong>: If the template requires signing, the DNS Provider looks up the URL signature keys in DNS.</li>
<li><strong>DNS Provider Checks Request URL Signature (if required)</strong>: The DNS Provider verifies the signature of the request URL.</li>
<li><strong>Service Provider Requests Authentication</strong>: The Service Provider requests authentication from the user.</li>
<li><strong>User Authenticates</strong>: The user authenticates with the DNS Provider.</li>
<li><strong>DNS Provider Checks Domain Name in Customer's Account</strong>: The DNS Provider verifies that the user is authorized to make change to the domain's DNS zone.</li>
<li><strong>DNS Provider Requests Consent for DNS Changes</strong>: The DNS Provider asks the user for consent to apply the changes to the DNS zone.</li>
<li><strong>User Confirms Consent</strong>: The user confirms their consent to the DNS changes.</li>
<li><strong>DNS Provider Applies Changes to DNS</strong>: The DNS Provider applies the changes to the zone.</li>
<li><strong>DNS Provider Redirects or Closes Window</strong>: The DNS Provider either redirects the user back to the Service Provider or closes the Domain Connect browser window.</li>
<li><strong>Service Provider Queries DNS Records</strong>: The Service Provider queries the DNS records to verify that the changes have been applied.</li>
<li><strong>DNS Server Returns New DNS Records</strong>: The DNS Server returns the updated DNS records.</li>
<li><strong>Service Provider Reports Success</strong>: The Service Provider reports to the user that the domain has been successfully connected to the service.</li>
</ol>
</section>

<section anchor="_6482cff6-83f7-14d3-c975-19039507c115"><name>The Asynchronous Flow</name>

<t anchor="_dbf9294e-d0db-0765-dc45-9f11d6fff4f4">The asynchronous OAuth flow is tailored for the Service Provider that wishes to make changes to DNS asynchronously with respect to the user interaction, or wishes to make multiple or additional changes to DNS over time.</t>

<figure anchor="_a925a8f1-52c5-d7b6-d11a-4bf0be38e70a">

<name>Sequence diagram of Asynchronous Flow</name><artwork type="ascii-art"><![CDATA[       ,-.
       `-'
       /|\
        |     ,----------------.   ,------------.          ,----------.
       / \    |Service Provider|   |DNS Provider|          |DNS Server|
      User    `--------+-------'   `------+-----'          `-----+----'
        .              .                  .                      .
        .        Steps 1-14 same as for Synchronous flow         .
        .              .                  .                      .
        |              |                  |                      |
        |              |                  |                      |
        |    15 Requests consent for      |                      |
        |    (future) DNS changes         |                      |
        |<--------------------------------|                      |
        |              |                  |                      |
        |       16 Grants consent         |                      |
        |-------------------------------->|                      |
        |              |                  |                      |
        |             17 Provides OAuth code                     |
        |              |<-----------------|                      |
        |              |                  |                      |
        |          18 Exchanges code for token                   |
        |              |----------------->|                      |
        |              |                  |                      |
        |            19 Returns access token                     |
        |              |<-----------------|                      |
        .              .                  .                      .
        .              .          Later   .                      .
        .              .                  .                      .
        .        20 Sends API request with token                 .
        |              |----------------->|                      |
        |              |                  |                      |
        |              |                  21 Apply changes to DNS|
        |              |                  |--------------------->|
        |              |                  |                      |
        |              22 Respond success |                      |
        |              |<-----------------|                      |
        |              |                  |                      |
        |              |          23 Query DNS records           |
        |              |---------------------------------------->|
        |              |                  |                      |
        |              |           24 New DNS records            |
        |              |<----------------------------------------|
        |              |                  |                      |
   25 Report success (async)              |                      |
        |<- - - - - - -|                  |                      |]]></artwork></figure>

<t anchor="_b69ab297-5e35-b219-4339-fcf0d325dc36">Steps:</t>

<t anchor="_385a7e18-0c15-426b-c7d1-77e78958b56f">1-14: Same as for the Synchronous Flow.</t>

<ol anchor="_03337003-ffc1-12a5-e8ae-79776360a4e8" type="1" start="15"><li><strong>DNS Provider Requests Consent for (Future) DNS Changes</strong>: The DNS Provider asks the user for consent to allow the Service Provider to make DNS changes on their behalf in the future.</li>
<li><strong>User Grants Consent</strong>: The user grants consent for future DNS changes.</li>
<li><strong>DNS Provider Provides OAuth Code</strong>: The DNS Provider provides an OAuth code to the Service Provider.</li>
<li><strong>Service Provider Exchanges Code for Token</strong>: The Service Provider exchanges the OAuth code for an access token.</li>
<li><strong>DNS Provider Returns Access Token</strong>: The DNS Provider provides an access token to the Service Provider.</li>
<li><strong>Service Provider Sends API Request with Token (Later)</strong>: At a later time, the Service Provider uses the access token to send an API request to apply the template to the domain.</li>
<li><strong>DNS Provider Applies Changes to DNS</strong>: The DNS Provider applies the changes to the DNS zone.</li>
<li><strong>DNS Provider Responds with Success</strong>: The DNS Provider responds to the Service Provider with success.</li>
<li><strong>Service Provider Queries DNS Records</strong>: The Service Provider queries the DNS records to verify that the changes have been applied.</li>
<li><strong>DNS Server Returns New DNS Records</strong>: The DNS Server returns the updated DNS records.</li>
<li><strong>Service Provider Reports Success (Asynchronous)</strong>: The Service Provider reports to the user that the domain has been successfully connected to the service.</li>
</ol>
</section>
</section>
    <section anchor="_9dbcad44-68da-d135-8005-687481bd2eb7"><name>DNS Provider Discovery</name>

<t anchor="_38ab0a04-a9e6-43fc-0698-4e769fbbbdc7">To facilitate discovery of the DNS Provider from a domain name DNS is utilized. This is done by returning a TXT record for  <tt>_domainconnect</tt> in the zone.</t>

<t anchor="_b65e587e-717d-9e86-7d97-daf54a74c23c">The record content represents an authority and path part of the settings REST API URL.</t>

<t anchor="_6b441875-64c9-4a1c-1958-429006047068">An example of the contents of this record:</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_d7f66d6c-7674-2919-4912-91a2e7454e22"><![CDATA[domainconnect.virtucondomains.example]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_0840e396-11d8-f593-9177-59365edcac4c"><tt>_domainconnect</tt> TXT record content, when prepended with <tt>https://</tt> schema and appended with <tt>/v2</tt> path segment, MUST form a valid URL <xref target="RFC3986" section="" relative=""></xref>. <tt>_domainconnect</tt> TXT record MUST contain the authority part of the URL and MAY contain a path part. <tt>_domainconnect</tt> MUST not contain schema, query or fragment part of an URL.</t>

<t anchor="_82a38b2c-024b-f5e5-02cb-e86fd66f73d7">As a practical matter of implementation, the DNS Provider may or may not contain a copy of this data in each and every zone. Instead, the DNS Provider MUST simply respond to the DNS query for the _`domainconnect` TXT record with the appropriate data.</t>

<t anchor="_76fcb4f0-c970-374f-9aaf-46e58da405e5">How this is implemented is up to the DNS Provider.</t>

<t anchor="_52690cc3-bb92-4ea2-090e-1c3deedbe5c4">For example, the DNS Provider may not store the data inside a TXT record for the domain, opting instead to put a CNAME in the zone and have the TXT record in the target of the CNAME. Another DNS Provider may simply respond with the appropriate records at the DNS layer without having the data in each zone.</t>

<t anchor="_4a857dbb-0fea-3711-e814-7599e1a4d2aa">The URL prefix returned MUST be subsequently used by the Service Provider to determine the additional settings for using Domain Connect on this domain at the DNS Provider. This is done by calling a REST API.</t>

<t anchor="_0b383708-468f-84f6-fc93-2508e423d150">Normative URI template of the settings end-point per <xref target="RFC6570" section="" relative=""></xref>:</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_536064f2-bdc1-8b1e-22ae-0cd4cf3f35ac"><![CDATA[GET

https://{+_domainconnect}/v2/{domain}/settings]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_4152f584-0c09-3dd8-8728-0ccbd4aad01b"><tt>_domainconnect</tt> parameter is the URL prefix returned in the _domainconnect TXT record.</t>

<t anchor="_08cac2b8-ea1d-6241-27f1-e3f8d98b14cd">This MUST return a JSON structure containing the settings to use for Domain Connect on the domain name (passed in on the path) at the DNS Provider. This JSON structure MUST contain the following fields unless otherwise specified.</t>

<table anchor="_b95f3055-688a-2898-d3c4-76210f776a1c"><name>properties of the settings data structure</name><thead><tr><th align="left"><strong>Field</strong></th><th align="left"><strong>Key</strong></th><th align="left"><strong>Type</strong></th><th align="left"><strong>Description</strong></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><strong>Provider Id</strong></td><td align="left">providerId</td><td align="left">String</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) Unique identifier for the DNS Provider. To ensure non-coordinated uniqueness, this SHOULD be the domain name of the DNS Provider (e.g. virtucom.example).</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Provider Name</strong></td><td align="left">providerName</td><td align="left">String</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) The name of the DNS Provider.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Provider Display Name</strong></td><td align="left">providerDisplayName</td><td align="left">String</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) The name of the DNS Provider that SHOULD be displayed by the Service Provider. This MAY change per domain for some DNS Providers that power multiple brands.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>UX URL Prefix for Synchronous Flows</strong></td><td align="left">urlSyncUX</td><td align="left">String</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) The URL Prefix for linking to the UX of Domain Connect for the synchronous flow at the DNS Provider. If not returned, the DNS Provider is not supporting the synchronous flow on this domain. This URL MUST be of  <tt>https</tt> schema and MUST NOT contain query or fragment part.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>UX URL Prefix for Asynchronous Flows</strong></td><td align="left">urlAsyncUX</td><td align="left">String</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) The URL Prefix for linking to the UX elements of Domain Connect for the asynchronous flow at the DNS Provider. If not returned, the DNS Provider is not supporting the asynchronous flow on this domain. This URL MUST be of  <tt>https</tt> schema and MUST NOT contain query or fragment part.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>API URL Prefix</strong></td><td align="left">urlAPI</td><td align="left">String</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) The URL Prefix for the REST API This URL MUST be of  <tt>https</tt> schema and MUST NOT contain query or fragment part.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Width of Window</strong></td><td align="left">width</td><td align="left">Number</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) This is the desired width of the window for granting consent when navigated in a popup. Default value if not returned is 750px. The Service Providers SHOULD obey to this setting if opening a pop-up window to assure optimal display of the user interface of the DNS Proviver.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Height of Window</strong></td><td align="left">height</td><td align="left">Number</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) This is the desired height of the window for granting consent when navigated in a popup. Default value if not returned is 750px. The Service Providers SHOULD obey to this setting if opening a pop-up window to assure optimal display of the user interface of the DNS Proviver.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>UX URL Control Panel</strong></td><td align="left">urlControlPanel</td><td align="left">String</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) This is a URL to the control panel for editing DNS at the DNS Provider. This field allows a Service Provider whose template isn't supported at the DNS Provider to provide a direct link to perform manual edits.  To allow deep links to the specific domain, this string MAY contain  <tt>%domain%</tt> which MUST be replaced with the domain name when building the deep link to the control panel of a given domain.  This URL MUST be of  <tt>https</tt> schema and MAY contain query or fragment part.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Name Servers</strong></td><td align="left">nameServers</td><td align="left">String List</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) This is the list of nameservers desired by the DNS Provider for the zone to be authoritative. This does not indicate the authoritative nameservers; for this the registry would be queried.</td></tr></tbody></table>

<sourcecode anchor="_3e76d46e-aead-d0a7-def3-340bc5e2fe63" type="json"><![CDATA[{
    "providerId": "virtucondomains.example",
    "providerName": "Virtucon Domains",
    "providerDisplayName": "Virtucon Domains",
    "urlSyncUX": "https://domainconnect.virtucondomains.example",
    "urlAsyncUX": "https://domainconnect.virtucondomains.example",
    "urlAPI": "https://api.domainconnect.virtucondomains.example",
    "width": 750,
    "height": 750,
    "urlControlPanel": "https://domaincontrolpanel.virtucondomains.ex
    ample/?domain=%domain%",
    "nameServers": ["ns01.virtucondomainsdns.example", "ns02.virtucon
    domainsdns.example"]
}]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_0e7a8d8a-3a77-f16a-79dc-38111d6c972b">Discovery MUST work on the Zone Apex only. Bear in mind that zones can be delegated to other users, making this information valuable to Service Providers since DNS changes may be different for a Zone Apex vs. a Sub Domain for an individual service.</t>

<t anchor="_4c51f655-d496-14b7-0d78-fa7a29e9e8df">The Service Provider MUST handle the condition when a query for the <tt>_domainconnect</tt> TXT record suceeds, but a call to query for the JSON fails. This can happen if the zone is hosted with another DNS Provider, but contains an incorrect  <tt>_domainconnect</tt> TXT record.</t>

<t anchor="_052e8158-0028-7255-a455-ca008db55192">The DNS Provider MUST return a 404 HTTP error code if they do not contain the zone.</t>

<table anchor="_14049357-6f3a-1de7-18dd-9ca5589dcdad"><name>HTTP status codes for the settings end-point</name><thead><tr><th align="left">Status</th><th align="left">Response</th><th align="left">Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><strong>Success</strong></td><td align="left">2xx</td><td align="left">A response of an http status code of 2xx indicates that the call was successful. The response is the JSON described above.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Not Found</strong></td><td align="left">404</td><td align="left">A response of a 404 indicates that the DNS Provider does not have the zone.</td></tr></tbody></table>
</section>
    <section anchor="_4b69ab94-9a9b-ddfb-7690-ceabba55a16c"><name>Applying Domain Connect</name>

<section anchor="_87be5e71-83dd-a3db-c804-4e182760c60e"><name>Endpoints</name>

<t anchor="_2fb9c7e8-a7df-d53f-090d-4e0872835145">The Domain Connect endpoints returned in the JSON during discovery are in the form of URLs.</t>

<t anchor="_634d9e11-0470-631d-b441-ea57d65e9407">The first set of endpoints are for the UX that the Service Provider links to. These are for the synchronous flow where the user can click to grant consent and have changes applied, and for the asynchronous OAuth flow where the user can grant consent for OAuth access.</t>

<t anchor="_1127f74d-dc14-3393-8efa-5ceb37833eb3">The second set of endpoints are for the REST API.</t>

<t anchor="_aadc8c52-de86-52e5-7e55-2f2de5c545e4">All endpoints begin with a root URL for the DNS Provider such as:</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_10bd3a78-dda4-f878-ff46-165ef44f3757"><![CDATA[https://connect.dnsprovider.example]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_aedff348-5850-e042-e25d-396924eebd30">They MAY also include any path segment at the discretion of the DNS Provider. For example:</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_1a7610ea-aeff-1d1e-6e5c-9408fab400c5"><![CDATA[https://connect.dnsprovider.example/api]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_dc11f935-863d-31d2-2053-3837b80747f9">The root URLs for the UX endpoints and the API endpoints are returned in the JSON payload during DNS Provider discovery.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="_c7e79aa8-0000-da69-f0ab-d67b95ff9f29"><name>Query Supported Template</name>

<t anchor="_af41240a-b567-068c-834d-d06c827ba840">Normative URI template of the template query end-point per <xref target="RFC6570" section="" relative=""></xref>:</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_85118722-3127-4b97-0c7d-707ed81ccd15"><![CDATA[GET

{+urlAPI}/v2/domainTemplates/providers/{providerId}/services
/{serviceId}]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_59cee358-50d8-13ae-232b-0022000a0c8b">This URL is be used by the Service Provider to determine if the DNS Provider supports a specific template.</t>

<t anchor="_9e37f378-8ea2-c4e5-b94d-3e5dfbe2a996">The following table describes the parameters of the URI template:</t>

<table anchor="_168fb19a-50a3-260f-d0ab-5174d0b497ed"><name>URI template parameters for the query supported template end-point</name><thead><tr><th align="left">Property</th><th align="left">Key</th><th align="left">Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><strong>URL API</strong></td><td align="left">urlAPI</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) Value of urlAPI from the settings endpoint.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Service Provider Id</strong></td><td align="left">providerId</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) identifier of the Service Provider of the template.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Service Id</strong></td><td align="left">serviceId</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) The name or identifier of the template.</td></tr></tbody></table>

<t anchor="_5135049a-581f-fd40-7160-7055b931275a">Returning a status of 200 without a body indicates the template is supported. The DNS Provider MAY disclose the version of the template in a JSON object with field  <tt>version</tt> (see: <xref target="template-definition">version field</xref> or the full JSON object of deployed template.</t>

<t anchor="_f11a7c0a-41e8-a437-942b-8ba0ea44c6d3">Returning a status of 404 indicates the template is not supported.</t>

<table anchor="_f22b9b52-6de2-1a70-d3a8-f9ab67f6b60a"><name>https status codes for the Query Supported Template end-point</name><thead><tr><th align="left">Status</th><th align="left">Response</th><th align="left">Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><strong>Success</strong></td><td align="left">2xx</td><td align="left">A response of an http status code of 2xx indicates that the call was successful. The response OPTIONALLY contains the version or template.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Not Found</strong></td><td align="left">404</td><td align="left">A response of a 404 indicates that the template is not supported</td></tr></tbody></table>
</section>

<section anchor="_abad4760-3c1a-d4d8-313e-652d764d2e5a"><name>Synchronous Flow</name>

<section anchor="_b80df814-5371-ecb4-d688-5d77580ba1d4"><name>Apply Template</name>

<section anchor="_41405f65-57be-2f72-3267-4b044a4dd407"><name>Apply Template URL</name>

<t anchor="_0b9ed2bc-81d8-5eb2-0e31-cff635a20838">Normative URI template of the synchronous template apply end-point per <xref target="RFC6570" section="" relative=""></xref>:</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_fbdf79e3-789a-5f6b-109f-d5850fd2309b"><![CDATA[GET

{+urlSyncUX}/v2/domainTemplates/providers/{providerId}/services
/{serviceId}/apply{?domain,host,groupId,force,providerName,
serviceName,instanceId,redirect_uri,properties*}{&sig,key}]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_4abd5dc7-19bc-3c1c-2433-a4bd5f3c2717">This is the URL, where the user agent (typically web browser) is sent to apply a template to a dns zone the user controls. It is redirected to or linked from the Service Provider to start the synchronous Domain Connect Protocol.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="_27a9701f-42a3-861f-ee3d-54143f280f8e"><name>Parameters/properties</name>

<table anchor="_f4b208a0-bcbf-5a5c-8ac6-11d090ce24f0"><name>URI template parameters of the apply call in the sync flow</name><thead><tr><th align="left">Property</th><th align="left">Request Parameter</th><th align="left">Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><strong>URL Sync UX</strong></td><td align="left">urlSyncUX</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) Value of urlSyncUX property from the settings endpoint.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Service Provider Id</strong></td><td align="left">providerId</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) identifier of the Service Provider of the template to be applied</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Service Id</strong></td><td align="left">serviceId</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) identifier of the template to be applied</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Domain</strong></td><td align="left">domain</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) The domain name being configured. This is the Zone Apex (the registered domain or delegated zone).</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Host</strong></td><td align="left">host</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) This is the host name of the Sub Domain. If left blank, the template is being applied to the Zone Apex. Otherwise the template is applied to the sub domain of the domain in the same zone.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Redirect URI</strong></td><td align="left">redirect_uri</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) The location to direct the client browser to upon successful authorization, or upon error. If omitted the DNS Provider SHOULD close the browser window upon completion. It MUST be scoped to the <tt>syncRedirectDomain</tt> authority from the template, or the request MUST be signed.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>State</strong></td><td align="left">state</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) A random and unique string passed along to prevent CSRF, or to pass back state. It MUST be returned as a query parameter when redirecting to the  <tt>redirect_uri</tt> described above.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Name/Value Pairs</strong></td><td align="left">properties</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) Any key that will be used as a replacement for the "% surrounded" variables in the template. The name portion of this API call corresponds to the variable(s) specified in the template and the value corresponds to the value that will be used when applying the template.<br /> The client MUST ignore any unknown parameters, not referenced in the template.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Provider Name</strong></td><td align="left">providerName</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) This parameter allows for the caller to provide additional text for display with the template providerName. This text SHOULD be used to augment the providerName value from the template, not replace it. This parameter is only allowed when the <tt>"sharedProviderName"</tt> attribute is set in the template. Note: this used to be controlled by the <tt>"shared"</tt> attribute in the template, which has been deprecated.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Service Name</strong></td><td align="left">serviceName</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) This parameter allows for the caller to provide additional text for display with the template  <tt>serviceName</tt>. It SHOULD be used to augment the <tt>serviceName</tt> value from the template, not replace it. This parameter is only allowed when the <tt>"sharedServiceName"</tt> attribute is set in the template.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Group Id</strong></td><td align="left">groupId</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) This parameter specifies the groups from the template to apply. If no group is specified, all groups are applied. Multiple groups MAY be specified in a comma delimited format.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Signature</strong></td><td align="left">sig</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) A signature of the query string. See Security Considerations section below.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Key</strong></td><td align="left">key</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) A value containing the host in DNS where the public key for the signature can be obtained. The domain for this host is in the template in syncPubKeyDomain. See Security Considerations section below.</td></tr></tbody></table>

<t anchor="_e620673e-668a-8094-a0fa-e0f1e2e4e387">An example query string:</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_c4d7ba6a-e044-c5bf-4e96-bdac35a6cae0"><![CDATA[GET

https://web-connect.dnsprovider.example/v2/domainTemplates/providers/
exampleservice.example/services/template1/apply?domain=example.com&
IP=192.168.42.42&RANDOMTEXT=shm%3A1542108821%3AHello]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_6625dd64-3613-e68b-d32e-918d9ae5ee22">This call indicates that the Service Provider wishes to connect the domain example.com to the service using the template identified by the composite key of the provider (exampleservice.example) and the service template owned by them (template1). In this example, there are two variables in this template, "IP" and "RANDOMTEXT". These variables are passed as name/value pairs.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="_6ca62226-b345-65b8-8e85-27454fa7b66b"><name>Browser handling considerations</name>

<t anchor="_0fc14723-e5b6-c5b6-82f6-ac92cd4d63d7">The synchronous template apply URL can be called in one of two ways.</t>

<section anchor="_32c26ec0-f5da-4b21-0345-93a847081eb6"><name>New Browser Window</name>

<t anchor="_9bcc6e07-e2c9-d106-e624-14ec50d0a5ac">The first is through a new browser tab or in a popup browser window. The DNS Provider authenticates the user if necessary, verifies domain ownership, and asks for confirmation before application of the template. After application of the template, the DNS Provider should automatically close the browser tab or window.</t>

<t anchor="_7ba78189-870b-8086-b0c8-b036b7e4fa64">Please note that in this case the only way Service Provider would know if the user has completed the setup or cancelled the operation is if the user closes the browser window. The Service Provider needs to verify via DNS what actually happened (See: <xref target="verification-of-changes"></xref>).</t>
</section>

<section anchor="_bf3f6c69-9cff-740a-3e63-1c4de3d4cf02"><name>Same Browser Window</name>

<t anchor="_ffbdc8c3-58c7-9819-3c91-a1e5c90f0e6b">The second is in the current browser tab/window. As above the DNS Provider authenticates the user in if necessary, verifies the user control of the DNS Zone for the domain, and asks for confirmation before application of the template. After application of the template (or cancellation by the user), the DNS Provider must redirect the browser to a return URL (redirect_uri query parameter of the Apply Template URL).</t>

<t anchor="_635e1397-a109-b531-c1c0-0bf0a2408632">Several parameters must be appended to the end of this redirect_uri.</t>

<ul anchor="_a56f8252-4755-ae07-9aec-724dc55aa49e"><li><t anchor="_bfe0953b-e46a-e4d4-e385-c6a9fc8406f2">State</t>
<t anchor="_47a20378-1fb5-37e5-51a6-5695b80deee6">If a state parameter is passed in on the query string, this must be passed back as state= on the redirect_uri.</t>
</li>
<li><t anchor="_bdd8b918-6b0b-7f81-1dc9-03880cb33bdc">Error</t>
<t anchor="_b113d19e-8128-0652-3dd3-86f671e5892c">If authorization could not be obtained or an error has occurred, the parameter error= must be appended. For consistency with the asynchronous OAuth flows the valid values for the error parameter will be as specified in OAuth 2.0  <xref target="RFC6749" section="" relative=""></xref> (4.1.2.1. Error Response - "error" parameter). Valid values are: invalid_request, unauthorized_client, access_denied, unsupported_response_type, invalid_scope, server_error, and temporarily_unavailable.</t>
</li>
<li><t anchor="_5c396be8-cf21-68ee-bda7-599ff6a1f518">Error Description</t>
<t anchor="_e981e8a3-ce68-393a-c269-e00c716d0c4f">When an error occurs, an OPTIONAL error description containing a developer focused error description may be returned.</t>

<t anchor="_6cf10249-01c0-883f-d5db-82618a701ab0">Under normal operation the access_denied error can be returned for a number of reasons. For example, the user may not have access to the account that owns the domain. Even if they do and successfully sign-in, the account or the domain may be suspended.</t>

<t anchor="_99ca492d-d0f0-22df-9c55-205cc7a21637">It is unlikely that the DNS Provider would want to leak this information to the Service Provider, and as such the description may be vague.</t>

<t anchor="_00b24f9f-6485-f1ae-ba68-a3a6fc01f44b">There is one piece of information that may be interesting to communicate to the Service Provider. This is when the end user decided to cancel the operation. If the DNS Provider wishes to communicate this to the Service Provider, when the error=access_denied the error_description may contain the prefix "user_cancel". Again, this is left to the discretion of the DNS Provider.</t>
</li>
</ul>

<t anchor="_1eb2d8a1-1ce5-456d-ccf7-d613332fd3a0">To prevent an open redirect, unless the request is digitally signed the redirect_uri must be within the domains specified in the template in syncRedirectDomain.</t>

<t anchor="_a97f6e50-9b9a-7a11-c553-8f0c7dc2a376">Please note that even though in this case Service Provider is informed whether the process finished without error, by receiving request to redirect_uri without error parameter, the Service Provider still SHOULD verify via DNS to be sure that the changes have been applied (See: <xref target="verification-of-changes"></xref>).</t>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="_c7f798f6-28e3-bd5a-5508-14846dc73825"><name>Security Considerations</name>

<section anchor="_6e285598-8db9-4a65-2375-10045254475d"><name>Risk of phishing with open template parameters</name>

<t anchor="_117fd3d5-30bb-c386-4e04-fee327227b72">By applying a template with parameters there is a security consideration that must be taken into account.</t>

<t anchor="_f6925fca-0214-c862-3603-45d8f3abc8ff">Consider the template above where the IP address of the A record is passed in through a variable. A bad actor could generate a URL with a malicious IP and phish users by sending out emails asking them to "re-configure" their service. If an end user is convinced to click on this link, they would land on the DNS Provider site to confirm the change. To the user, this would appear to be a valid request to configure the domain. Yet the IP would be hijacking the service.</t>

<t anchor="_c0185d1d-5e2f-927d-0c75-c04e7c748c1b">Not all templates have this problem. But when they do, there are several options.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="_e90531f1-bae2-c5e2-ae3c-537ad1553779"><name>Disable Synchronous</name>

<t anchor="_b4cfc016-7d00-45c8-2891-0eeb648a8079">One option is to disable the synchronous flow and use asynchronous OAuth. This can be controlled with the  <tt>syncBlock</tt> value from the template. However, as will be seen below OAuth has a higher implementation burden and requires onboarding between each Service and DNS Provider.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="_bfa0da01-0e41-7318-10b0-20bc05a33974"><name>Digitally Sign Requests</name>

<t anchor="_74b69b65-b237-538f-e546-449814aae5a0">Another option is to digitally sign the query string. A signature is appended as an additional query string parameter, properly URL encoded and of the form:</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_0e2aff8b-e201-bbc7-c19d-cac070102abd"><![CDATA[sig=V2te9zWMU7G3plxBTsmYSJTvn2vzMvNwAjWQ%2BwTe91DxuJhdVf4cVc4vZBYfEYV
7u5d7PzTO7se7OrkhyiB7TpoJJW1yB5qHR7HKM5SZldUsdtg5%2B1SzEtIX0Uq8b2mCmQ
F%2FuJGXpqCyFrEajvpTM7fFKPk1kuctmtkjV7%2BATcvNPLWY7KyE4%2Bqc8jpfN61cP
5l8iA4krAa3%2BfTro5cmWR8YUJ5yrnRs6KT4b5D71HFvOUk0sGEUddUUlsyRQKRHUFN6
HjEya50YDHfZJlYHkHlK0xX6Yqeii9QZ2I35U9eJbSvZGQko5beqviWFXdsVDbvd3DYcb
SHgJq9%2FXoMTTw%3D%3D]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_3918b14e-607f-d9d8-763c-8ee933f8d0cc">The Service Provider generates this signature using a private key. As indicated, this signature is generated from the query string properly URL encoded.</t>

<t anchor="_882483cd-8ae6-1e9f-5527-9698f9d9278d">The Service Provider MUST publish their public key and place it in a DNS TXT record in a domain specified in the template in <tt>syncPubKeyDomain</tt> at a host of their choice. The TXT record MUST be published as a comma-separated list of key-value properties.</t>

<table anchor="_1d5f468a-9063-026b-8a6b-5b3751f4894f"><name>Properties of the public key TXT record</name><thead><tr><th align="left">Property</th><th align="left">Key</th><th align="left">Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><strong>Fragment Index</strong></td><td align="left">p</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) The index value of the public key fragment</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Fragment Payload</strong></td><td align="left">d</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) The payload of public key fragment</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Signing Algorithm</strong></td><td align="left">a</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) The parameter identifies the algorithm intended for use with the key. The values used SHALL be registered in the IANA "JSON Web Signature and Encryption Algorithms" registry established by <xref target="RFC7518" section="" relative=""></xref>. If omitted it MUST be assumed to be RS256. The support of RS256 is MANDATORY for both DNS Providers and Service Providers.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Public Key Format</strong></td><td align="left">t</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) The format of the public key. If omitted MUST be assumed to be x509.</td></tr></tbody></table>

<t anchor="_465292db-9faf-5e07-6d43-0fd45ddbff8d">To allow for key rotation or usage of multiple keys, the host name of the TXT record MUST be appended as another query parameter on the query string of the form:</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_eb673c14-384c-a4d3-3f5a-24de38394c4f"><![CDATA[key=_dcpubkeyv1]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_60ee8286-1d2c-7be1-9104-cd2bfe16e933">This example indicates that the public key can be found by doing a DNS query for a TXT record called _dcpubkeyv1 in the domain specified in the <tt>syncPubKeyDomain</tt> from the template.</t>

<t anchor="_150708f8-24ce-d799-8a90-681ab57de84a">To account for DNS Servers with limits to the size of a TXT record, the public key MAY be split into multiple TXT records at the specified host. For example, a public key of:</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_1ceaff73-60f8-39ce-b839-ad72aac76f83"><![CDATA[MIIBIjANBgkqhkiG9w0BAQEFAAOCAQ8AMIIBCgKCAQEA18SgvpmeasN4BHkkv0SBjAzIc
4grYLjiAXRtNiBUiGUDMeTzQrKTsWvy9NuxU1dIHCZy9o1CrKNg5EzLIZLNyMfI6qiXnM
+HMd4byp97zs/3D39Q8iR5poubQcRaGozWx8yQpG0OcVdmEVcTfyR/XSEWC5u16EBNvRn
NAOAvZYUdWqVyQvXsjnxQot8KcK0QP8iHpoL/1dbdRy2opRPQ2FdZpovUgknybq/6FkeD
tW7uCQ6Mvu4QxcUa3+WP9nYHKtgWip/eFxpeb+qLvcLHf1h0JXtxLVdyy6OLk3f2JRYUX
2ZZVDvG3biTpeJz6iRzjGg6MfGxXZHjI8weDjXrJwIDAQAB]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_40ea340b-c62e-6019-5e4b-8940ed026cf7">may contain several TXT records. The records would be of the form:</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_cca3dc49-79a8-f681-8fc2-fd9cc62cc842"><![CDATA[p=1,a=RS256,d=MIIBIjANBgkqhkiG9w0BAQEFAAOCAQ8AMIIBCgKCAQEA18SgvpmeasN
4BHkkv0SBjAzIc4grYLjiAXRtNiBUiGUDMeTzQrKTsWvy9NuxU1dIHCZy9o1CrKNg5EzL
IZLNyMfI6qiXnM+HMd4byp97zs/3D39Q8iR5poubQcRaGozWx8yQpG0OcVdmEVcTfy

p=2,a=RS256,d=R/XSEWC5u16EBNvRnNAOAvZYUdWqVyQvXsjnxQot8KcK0QP8iHpoL/1
dbdRy2opRPQ2FdZpovUgknybq/6FkeDtW7uCQ6Mvu4QxcUa3+WP9nYHKtgWip/eFxpeb+
qLvcLHf1h0JXtxLVdyy6OLk3f2JRYUX2ZZVDvG3biTpeJz6iRzjGg6MfGxXZHjI8

p=3,a=RS256,d=weDjXrJwIDAQAB]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_dcc2a64b-2187-45fe-630a-7026817dff11">Here the public key is broken into three records in DNS, and the data also indicates that the signing algorithm is an RSA Signature with SHA-256. The representation as x509 certificate is the default in this case.</t>

<t anchor="_e485afca-ea0c-4b84-9341-6a1bea396241">The above data was generated for a query string:</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_3aa14992-c7e6-441e-42e9-01b0b73b93b0"><![CDATA[a=1&b=2&ip=10.10.10.10&domain=example.net]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_5dd1fd0f-c6ae-a9ce-bd01-ad5ef96ecca4">Signing the query string by the Service Provider is OPTIONAL. Not all Services Provider templates require or are able to provide this level of security. Presence of the  <tt>syncPubKeyDomain</tt> in the template indicates that the template requires signature verification.</t>

<t anchor="_9481ecef-7cb0-50a0-5d54-84ff1d99c4ac">DNS Providers MUST reject any request to apply a template with <tt>syncPubKeyDomain</tt> present and no signing of a query string in place.</t>

<t anchor="_7e957a29-1750-3afc-c74a-787b505c01c4">The digital signature MUST be generated on the full query string only, excluding the sig and key parameters. This is everything after the ?, except the sig and key values which MUST be appended to the signed query string.</t>

<t anchor="_440d7054-6ba9-c612-0230-af9296cab634">The values of each query string value key/value pair MUST be properly URL Encoded before the signature is generated.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="_d18f4598-26bf-9758-db0b-427fcb9bc518"><name>Warnings</name>

<t anchor="_a3c7832c-3dc0-a54d-191d-b0675694ceeb">Some applications aren't able to use OAuth and/or sign requests.</t>

<t anchor="_effefbd3-bd34-ed49-ea13-20f54f75ab4f">If the template require variables, and OAuth and signing isn't available, the flag  <tt>warnPhishing</tt> SHOULD be set to true in the template in order to offer transparency to the DNS Provider about security properties of the template.</t>

<t anchor="_9ff2848e-f295-7121-e261-1626d25333b5">When set this indicates to the DNS Provider that they SHOULD display additional warnings to the user to have them verify the link was/is from a reputable source before applying the template.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="_e76a1b69-fd98-6dc4-3d81-226cfc8eb4d7"><name>Shared Templates</name>

<t anchor="_9e7b05df-f42e-a89b-9ed1-ccd878adc70c">Some templates can be called by multiple companies, or be used for different purposes.</t>

<t anchor="_71396844-0e26-bacf-539c-4903571e311a">For example, most services are sold and provided by the same company. However, some Service Providers have a reseller channel. This allows the service to be provided by the Service Provider, but sold through third parties. It is often this third party reseller that configures DNS.</t>

<t anchor="_8c4238e2-b965-2e65-4c33-98964e2f5b10">While each reseller could enable Domain Connect, this is inefficient for the DNS Providers. Enabling a single template that is shared by multiple resellers would be more optimal.</t>

<t anchor="_29151cc0-5702-f1d4-4c51-4aa2fabcb5e0">As another example, some templates may be used for different purposes by the same company.</t>

<t anchor="_644b6795-5598-a534-c01a-bec71cdf8ab3">To facilitate these use cases, the ability to pass in additional context for the display of the providerName and serviceName is enabled. This is only allowed when the template enables the capability through the sharedProviderName and/or sharedServiceName flags.</t>

<t anchor="_625a4c5f-1605-e6a3-f97c-dc9bd5a65749">Note: The shared flag used to be used for this purpose, but has been deprecated.</t>

<t anchor="_a5a81f62-4685-e8e5-e33c-e7e5ca93ad62">The exact message presented to the user is up to the DNS Provider. However it is recommended that these fields be used to augment the display of the serviceName and providerName from the template, not replace it.</t>

<t anchor="_086e7b58-0d69-45be-c709-89dcb92df7d2">Note: When a Service Provider has a large reseller channel, it is highly recommended that the Service Provider creates an API for their resellers to ease the implementation of Domain Connect. There are elements of convenience in doing this around Domain Discovery and URL Formatting. But this would be required if the template required signatures.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="_fe8b0702-1481-25ec-3b6c-b589c4694dc3"><name>Asynchronous Flow: OAuth</name>

<section anchor="_f3b12f12-64c5-42b4-109f-9cff05c77c80"><name>General information</name>

<t anchor="_df0acadb-760d-6703-386e-58254827e2ba">Using the OAuth flow is a more advanced use case needed by Service Providers that have more complex configurations that may require multiple steps and/or are asynchronous from the user's interaction.</t>

<t anchor="_a47f636b-dd9b-b475-5982-bd95b954f7ad">Details of an OAuth implementation are beyond the scope of this specification. Instead, an overview of how OAuth is used by Domain Connect is given here.</t>

<t anchor="_3024ce6a-263b-a773-7ab5-fd7ab9348229">Not all DNS Providers will support the asyncronous flow. As such it is recommended that Service Providers relying on an OAuth implementation also implement a synchronous implementation.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="_e307e1e3-dedf-fa9c-608e-8a29c3f3e3f9"><name>OAuth Flow: Setup</name>

<t anchor="_0c76c1a0-241b-7210-8f47-5e241df64679">Service Providers wishing to use the OAuth flow MUST register as an OAuth client with each DNS Provider. This is typically a manual process, however other solutions like OAuth Dynamic Client Registration  <xref target="RFC7591" section="" relative=""></xref> MAY be offered by DNS Provider as well.</t>

<t anchor="_6cf14f0a-fe8d-be88-3602-084ca7f326ce">To register, the Service Provider would provide (in addition to their template) any configuration necessary for the DNS Providers OAuth implementation. This includes valid URLs and Domains for redirects upon success or errors of OAuth flow, token validity, presence and validity of refresh tokens etc.</t>

<t anchor="_b861124a-49fd-3b0f-5b57-3cbe729fb77d">Note: The validity of redirects are very important in any OAuth implementation. Most OAuth vulnerabilities are a combination of an open redirect and/or a compromised secret.</t>

<t anchor="_52632d66-45de-79c8-fb84-5d79826afaa8">The DNS Provider SHOULD give the Service Provider a client id and a secret which will be used when requesting tokens. For simplicity the client id MAY be the same as the providerId, however it is up to the agreement between the parties involved. Any other form of client authentication within OAuth framework MAY be agreed between the parties.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="_e05b10c1-e056-46be-7fa8-f93e083cdb1f"><name>OAuth Flow: Getting an Authorization Code</name>

<t anchor="_bfe8dd6d-71bb-a4b5-7b27-334e21e89d44">Normative URI template of the authorization code end-point per <xref target="RFC6570" section="" relative=""></xref>:</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_179cfb94-0755-61c7-f1bb-8190e711cc50" type="http"><![CDATA[GET

{+urlAsyncUX}/v2/domainTemplates/providers/{providerId}{?domain,host,
client_id,redirect_uri,response_type,scope,providerName,serviceName,
state,properties*}
}]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_c1be73ca-827c-d7a9-9192-ac0e1dca5bae">To initiate the OAuth flow the Service Provider first links to the DNS Provider to gain consent.</t>

<t anchor="_f54931a8-e2bc-6363-68ee-1179ffeed426">This endpoint is similar to the synchronous flow described above. The DNS Provider MUST authenticate the user, verify the user has control of the DNS Zone for the domain, and ask the user for permission. Instead of permission to make a change to DNS, the permission is now to allow the Service Provider to make the changes on their behalf. Similarly the DNS Provider MAY warn the user that (the eventual) application of a template might change existing records and/or disrupt existing services attached to the domain.</t>

<t anchor="_22e0616a-22d4-f3d7-5ca7-3ec6f7c9dd41">While the variables for the applied template would be provided later, the values of some variables may be necessary to determine conflicts. As such, any variables impacting conflicting records SHOULD be provided in the consent flow. This primarly includes variables in hosts, and variables in the data portion for certain TXT records.</t>

<t anchor="_0d5562b9-e5e2-92d2-b2e2-a67e6ce9ab04">The protocol allows for the Service Provider to gain consent to apply multiple templates. These templates are specified in the  <tt>scope</tt> parameter. It also allows for the Service Provider to gain consent to apply these templates to the domain or to the domain with multiple sub-domains. These are specified in the  <tt>domain</tt> and <tt>host</tt> parameter. If conflict detection is implemented by the DNS Provider, they SHOULD account for all permutations, in order to inform the end user of all possible consequences of the authorised change.</t>

<t anchor="_985391c1-ba55-ba70-901e-2cb224f6343e">The scope parameter is a space separated list (as per the OAuth protocol) of the template serviceIds. The host parameter is an OPTIONAL comma separated list of hosts. A blank entry for the host implies the template can be applied to the Zone Apex For example:</t>

<table anchor="_981fd134-ba86-f8e2-3072-4d7e0bebbcc6"><name>examples of scope and host parameter values in the async flow</name><thead><tr><th align="left"><strong>Query String</strong></th><th align="left"><strong>Description</strong></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><tt>scope=t1%20t2&#x26;domain=example.com</tt></td><td align="left">Templates "t1" and "t2" can be applied to example.com</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><tt>scope=t1%20t2&#x26;domain=example.com&#x26;host=sub1,sub2</tt></td><td align="left">Templates "t1" and "t2" can be applied to sub1.example.com or sub2.example.com</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><tt>scope=t1%20t2&#x26;domain=example.com&#x26;host=sub1,</tt></td><td align="left">Templates "t1" and "t2" can be applied to example.com or sub1.example.com</td></tr></tbody></table>

<t anchor="_d3e87e8c-fa4b-8660-1923-56dfbcc7c1ac">Upon successful authorization/verification/consent from the user, the DNS Provider MUST direct the end user's browser to the redirect URI. The authorization code MUST be appended to this URI as a query parameter of <tt>"code="</tt> as per the OAuth specification.</t>

<t anchor="_ec84424f-b96a-1ce8-936f-a71913849d4c">Similar to the synchronous flow, upon error the DNS Provider MAY append an error code as query parameter <tt>"error"</tt>. These errors are also from the OAuth 2.0 <xref target="RFC6749" section="" relative=""></xref> (4.1.2.1. Error Response - "error" parameter). Valid values include: <tt>invalid_request</tt>, <tt>unauthorized_client</tt>, <tt>access_denied</tt>, <tt>unsupported_response_type</tt>, <tt>invalid_scope</tt>, <tt>server_error</tt>, and <tt>temporarilly_unavailable</tt>. An OPTIONAL <tt>error_description</tt> suitable for developers may also be returned at the discretion of the DNS Provider. The same considerations as in the synchronous flow apply here.</t>

<t anchor="_e196b422-6941-a72c-aee4-70ac46fe7302">The state value passed into the call MUST be passed back on the query string as  <tt>state=</tt>.</t>

<t anchor="_8a348986-8231-e521-130b-c51ea35806b8">The following table describes the values of the URI template for the request for the OAuth consent flow that must be included unless otherwise indicated</t>

<table anchor="_9fd61df0-5cf1-b870-4473-9435c1871e1e"><name>URI template parameters of the authorization end-point in async flow</name><thead><tr><th align="left">Property</th><th align="left">Key</th><th align="left">Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><strong>URL Sync UX</strong></td><td align="left">urlAsyncUX</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) Value of urlAsyncUX property from the settings endpoint.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Service Provider Id</strong></td><td align="left">providerId</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) identifier of the Service Provider of the template to be applied</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Domain</strong></td><td align="left">domain</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) The domain name being configured. This is the Zone Apex.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Host</strong></td><td align="left">host</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) An list of comma separated host names upon which the template may be applied. An empty string implies the root.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Client Id</strong></td><td align="left">client_id</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) The client id that was provided by the DNS Provider to the Service Provider during registration.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Redirect URI</strong></td><td align="left">redirect_uri</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) The location to direct the client's browser upon successful authorization or upon error. Validation of the redirect_uri MUST be done by the DNS Provider to match the values provided during onboarding.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Response type</strong></td><td align="left">response_type</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) If included it MUST be the string 'code' to indicate an authorization code is being requested.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Scope</strong></td><td align="left">scope</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) The OAuth scope corresponds to the requested templates. This is list of space separated serviceIds.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Provider Name</strong></td><td align="left">providerName</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) This parameter allows for the caller to provide additional text for display with the template providerName. This text SHOULD be used to augment the providerName value from the template, not replace it.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Service Name</strong></td><td align="left">serviceName</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) This parameter allows for the caller to provide additional text for display with the template serviceName(s). It SHOULD be used to augment the serviceName value(s) from the template, not replace.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>State</strong></td><td align="left">state</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) This is a random, unique string passed along to prevent CSRF or to pass state value back to the caller. If present it MUST be returned as a parameter appended to the <tt>redirect_url</tt> described above.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Name/Value Pairs</strong></td><td align="left">properties</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) Any key that will be used as a replacement for the "% surrounded" value(s) in a template required for conflict detection.<br /> This includes variables used in hosts and data in certain TXT records.</td></tr></tbody></table>
</section>

<section anchor="_8600ef50-5408-326a-0e7c-7414f07f3772"><name>OAuth Flow: Requesting an Access Token</name>

<t anchor="_119e201d-3e02-48af-d172-6c5be404ce41">Normative URI template of the access token end-point per <xref target="RFC6570" section="" relative=""></xref>:</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_079659a4-568b-833a-b43a-acba9bfb5415"><![CDATA[POST

{+urlAPI}/v2/oauth/access_token]]></sourcecode>


<table anchor="_60c1a26c-6a93-0d4d-e127-e91343d9040c"><name>URI template parameters of the access token end-point</name><thead><tr><th align="left">Property</th><th align="left">Request Parameter</th><th align="left">Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><strong>URL API</strong></td><td align="left">urlAPI</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) Value of urlAPI property from the settings endpoint.</td></tr></tbody></table>

<t anchor="_d579baf6-6b7e-74a2-cce3-e8bd0764850d">Once authorization has been granted, the Service Provider MUST use the Authorization Code provided to request an Access Token. The OAuth specification recommends that the Authorization Code be a short lived token, and a reasonable recommended setting is ten minutes, however the specific setup would depend on specifics of DNS Provider's implementation. As such this exchange needs to be completed before that time has expired or the process will need to be repeated.</t>

<t anchor="_a21a7bd7-7ad0-23c5-ce3a-e477699b8a02">This token exchange is typically done via a server to server API call from the Service Provider to the DNS Provider using a POST. When called in this manner a secret is provided along with the Authorization Code.</t>

<t anchor="_03cf9697-f7f8-439a-b28b-08c58b1374fa">OAuth does allow for retrieving the access token without a secret. This is typically done when the OAuth client is a client application. When onboarding with the DNS Provider this would need to be enabled.</t>

<t anchor="_681bf361-3c8e-f79e-b6c4-0d8196365602">When the secret is provided (which is the normal case), care must be taken. A malicious user could create a domain that returns a false _`domainconnect` TXT record, and subsequently a JSON call to their own server for the API end point. By doing so, they could then run Domain Connect on their domain and retrieve the secret.</t>

<t anchor="_880643fe-d3b9-1bd4-1e2b-fe9d21214cf3">As such the urlAPI used for OAuth by the Service Provider SHOULD be maintained per DNS Provider and not the value retrieved during discovery or other measures have to be implemented to prevent token leakage.</t>

<t anchor="_9ec6bc57-508f-cb79-4cc8-778349fb7f5b">The following table describes the POST parameters that MUST be included in the request for the access token unless otherwise indicated. The parameters SHALL be accepted via the query string or the body of the post. This is again particularly important for the  <tt>client_secret</tt>, as passing secrets via a query string is generally frowned upon given that various systems often log URLs.</t>

<t anchor="_afcea830-596e-7d08-78fa-c2909cc522af">The body of the post is application/json encoded.</t>

<table anchor="_8642054b-c084-b694-5631-7bc5c5154914"><name>parameters of the token end-point</name><thead><tr><th align="left">Property</th><th align="left">Key</th><th align="left">Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><strong>Authorization Code/Refresh Code</strong></td><td align="left">code/refresh_token</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) The authorization code that was provided in the previous step when the user accepted the authorization request, or the refresh_token for a subsequent access token.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Redirect URI</strong></td><td align="left">redirect_uri</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) This is REQUIRED if a redirect_uri was passed to request the authorization code. When included, it needs to be the same redirect_uri provided in this step.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Grant type</strong></td><td align="left">grant_type</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) The type of code in the request. Usually the string 'authorization_code' or 'refresh_token'</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Client ID</strong></td><td align="left">client_id</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) This is the client id that was provided by the DNS Provider to the Service Provider during registration</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Client Secret</strong></td><td align="left">client_secret</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) The secret provided to the Service Provider during registration. Typically required unless the rare circumstance with secret-less OAuth.</td></tr></tbody></table>

<t anchor="_be0f85e5-78e5-378e-526f-9a3fcbd24c6e">Upon successful token exchange, the DNS Provider MUST return a response with 4 properties in the body of the response.</t>

<table anchor="_8b0b3a1d-5c31-45b0-5e99-f285048d4255"><name>properties of the token end-point response</name><thead><tr><th align="left">Property</th><th align="left">Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><strong>access_token</strong></td><td align="left">The access token to be used when making API requests</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>token_type</strong></td><td align="left">Always the string "bearer"</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>expires_in</strong></td><td align="left">The number of seconds until the access_token expires</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>refresh_token</strong></td><td align="left">The token that can be used to request new access tokens when this one has expired.</td></tr></tbody></table>

<table anchor="_9c7a30b5-45af-fad1-15d2-a24e7c5d2de1"><name>http status codes of the token end-point response</name><thead><tr><th align="left">Status</th><th align="left">Response</th><th align="left">Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><strong>Success</strong></td><td align="left">2xx</td><td align="left">A response of an http status code of 2xx indicates that the call was successful. The response is the JSON described above.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Errors</strong></td><td align="left">4**</td><td align="left">All other responses indicate an error.</td></tr></tbody></table>
</section>

<section anchor="_f5b38039-0a19-24a6-0cba-98c11dbc54c1"><name>OAuth Flow: Making Requests with Access Tokens</name>

<t anchor="_4d9a53b1-4da0-51aa-3abe-fcb79b717bac">Once the Service Provider has the access token, they can call the DNS Provider's API to make changes to DNS on the domain by applying and (OPTIONALLY) removing authorized templates. These templates can be applied to the Zone Apex or to any Sub Domain that has been authorized.</t>

<t anchor="_8868268c-6aca-9cda-fb18-9988293d5074">All calls to this API pass the access token in the Authorization Header of the request to the call to the API. More details can be found in the OAuth specifications, but as an example:</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_a678a62a-1a1f-167f-5a75-0f7f9062755c"><![CDATA[GET /resource/1 HTTP/1.1

Host: example.com

Authorization: Bearer mF_9.B5f-4.1JqM]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_05de792c-da62-df02-a942-c7539459623b">While the calls below do not have the same security consideration of passing the secret, it is recommend that the urlAPI be from a stored value vs. the value returned during discovery here as well.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="_5da94e86-20a8-993a-9a0a-04a81440c243"><name>OAuth Flow: Apply Template to Domain.</name>

<t anchor="_e7bc8ca6-4f45-f28e-f4ef-fa63bfce8763">Normative URI template of the asynchronous apply end-point per <xref target="RFC6570" section="" relative=""></xref>:</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_aae58cf3-507b-3352-3d17-3cf913a2e8a0"><![CDATA[POST

{+urlAPI}/v2/domainTemplates/providers/{providerId}/services
/{serviceId}/apply{?domain,host,groupId,force,providerName,
serviceName,instanceId,properties*}]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_bc615b51-5fc3-96b1-0ce5-773b26fac9e2">The primary function of the API is to apply a template to a user domain.</t>

<t anchor="_7e0741b6-22f2-8485-14b7-8f9dd4e99f90">While the <tt>providerId</tt> is implied in the authorization, this is on the path for consistency with the synchronous flows and other APIs. If not matching what was authorized, an error MUST be returned.</t>

<t anchor="_75f3b3f3-e971-9dd7-900e-d3f2f047dd78">When applying a template to a domain, it is possible that a conflict may exist with previous settings. While it is recommended that conflicts be detected when the user grants consent, because OAuth is asynchronous it is possible that a new conflict was introduced by the user.</t>

<t anchor="_49dcb832-8f37-aff3-8df0-2bb321d6ff23">While it is up to the DNS Provider to determine what constitutes a conflict (see section on Conflicts below), when one is detected calling this API MUST return an error. This error SHOULD enumerate the conflicting records in a format described below.</t>

<t anchor="_e9a5fa8b-1aa9-70a6-09fe-2c705811a71b">Because the user often isn't present at the time of this error, it is up the Service Provider to determine how to handle this condition. Some providers may decide to notify the user. Others may decide to apply their template anyway using the <tt>"force"</tt> parameter. This parameter will bypass error checks for conflicts, and after the call the service will be in its desired state.</t>

<t anchor="_f5996a9a-249e-a64f-078b-950bf0604f04">Calls to apply a template via OAuth require the following parameters posted to the above URL unless otherwise indicated. The DNS Provider MUST accept parameters in query string or body of this post.</t>

<t anchor="_41be3c9e-f399-6066-aae6-2263bbd5ebca">The body is application/json encoded.</t>

<table anchor="_3ca83f65-4f4b-3290-86c3-6f95497a2cc2"><name>URI template parameters of the apply end-point in the async flow</name><thead><tr><th align="left">Property</th><th align="left">Key</th><th align="left">Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><strong>URL API</strong></td><td align="left">urlAPI</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) Value of urlAPI from the settings endpoint.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Service Provider Id</strong></td><td align="left">providerId</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) identifier of the Service Provider of the template to be applied</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Service Id</strong></td><td align="left">serviceId</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) The name or identifier of the template to be applied.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Domain</strong></td><td align="left">domain</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) The Zone Apex domain name being configured. It MUST match the domain that was authorized in the token.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Host</strong></td><td align="left">host</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) The host name of the Sub Domain that was authorized in the token. If omitted or left blank, the template is being applied to the Zone Apex.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Name/Value Pairs</strong></td><td align="left">*</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) Any variable fields consumed by this template. The name portion of this API call corresponds to the variable(s) specified in the record and the value corresponds to the value that MUST be used when applying the template as per the implementation notes.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Group ID</strong></td><td align="left">groupId</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) Specifies the group of changes in the template to apply. If omitted, all changes are applied. This can also be a comma separated list of groupIds.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Force</strong></td><td align="left">force</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) Specifies that the template SHOULD be applied independently of any conflicts that may exist on the domain. This can be a value of 0 or 1.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Provider Name</strong></td><td align="left">providerName</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) This parameter allows for the caller to provide additional context for the <tt>providerName</tt> that applied the template. It MAY be used by DNS Providers that want to display state regarding which templates have been applied. It is only allowed when the <tt>"sharedProviderName"</tt> attribute is set in the template being applied.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Service Name</strong></td><td align="left">serviceName</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) This parameter allows for the caller to provide additional context for the <tt>serviceName</tt> that applied the template. It MAY be used by DNS Providers that want to display state regarding which templates have been applied. It is only allowed when the <tt>"sharedProviderName"</tt> attribute is set in the template being applied.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>InstanceId</strong></td><td align="left">instanceId</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) Only applicable to templates supporting multiple instances (see  <xref target="template-definition">multiInstance</xref> template property). Allows for later removal of one template instance by DNS Providers storing this information.</td></tr></tbody></table>

<t anchor="_b5efe689-a711-15d6-3cec-e06fa5461c4c">An example call is below. In this example, it is contemplated that there are two variables in this template, <tt>"IP"</tt> and <tt>"RANDOMTEXT"</tt> which both require values. These variables are passed as name/value pairs.</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_8dc745c7-6b71-73e0-4b6c-b5e1ed9c731a"><![CDATA[POST

https://connect.dnsprovider.example/v2/domainTemplates/providers/
exampleservice.example/services/template1/apply?IP=192.0.2.42&
RANDOMTEXT=shm%3A1542108821%3AHello&force=1]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_8b4679cb-9fb0-2630-bd51-98b432fa7e62">The API MUST validate the access token, and that the domain belongs to the user and is represented by the token being presented. Any errors with variables, conflicting templates, or problems with the state of the domain are returned; otherwise the template is applied.</t>

<t anchor="_649ee89c-e803-4836-40b5-e3381b3accad">Results of this call can include information indicating success or an error. Errors MUST be 400 status codes, with the following codes defined.</t>

<table anchor="_dee8ca21-f065-cb39-d191-b9023bab968b"><name>http status codes of the apply end-point in the async flow</name><thead><tr><th align="left">Status</th><th align="left">Response</th><th align="left">Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><strong>Success</strong></td><td align="left">2xx</td><td align="left">Any 200 level code MUST be considered a success. The response MAY be of status 200 with a response body, but also 204 without a body.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Bad Request</strong></td><td align="left">400</td><td align="left">A response of a 400 indicates that the server cannot process the request because it was malformed or had errors. This response code is intended for programming errors.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Unauthorized</strong></td><td align="left">401</td><td align="left">A response of a 401 indicates that caller is not authorized to make this call. This can be because the token was revoked, or other access issues.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Conflict</strong></td><td align="left">409</td><td align="left">This indicates that the call was good, and the caller authorized, but the change could not be applied due to a conflicting template. Errors due to conflicts MUST NOT be returned when force is equal to 1.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Error</strong></td><td align="left">4xx</td><td align="left">Other 4xx error codes SHOULD be returned when something is wrong with the request that makes applying the template problematic; most often something that is wrong with the account and requires attention.</td></tr></tbody></table>

<t anchor="_fc99673d-3f9c-8b74-2ba0-cf05ac4ec87f">When a 409 is returned, the body of the response SHOULD contain details of the conflicting records. If present this MUST be JSON containing the error code, a message suitable for developers, and an array of tuples containing the conflicting records type, host, and data element.</t>

<t anchor="_411c900d-6e6f-91e3-8104-ef24e7b4ac78">As an example:</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_7ee51db3-3675-1991-a67e-3fcda36f1333" type="json"><![CDATA[{
    "code": "409",
    "message": "Conflicting records",
    "records": [
        {
            "type": "CNAME",
            "host": "www",
            "data": "@"
        },
        {
            "type": "A",
            "host": "@",
            "data": "random ip"
        }
    ]
}]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_2a65cc74-04c4-34b7-6b2f-902bb826f76c">In this example, the Service Provider tried to apply a new hosting template. The domain had an existing service applied for hosting.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="_200efd4e-1898-ffad-a72a-0d96959dcb1a"><name>OAuth Flow: Revert Template</name>

<t anchor="_0615bb1c-218f-9efb-7a4b-45b0c4568ba8">This call reverts the application of a specific template from a domain.</t>

<t anchor="_1f6a1b9e-089d-3f75-fe0a-cc5790f7aae0">Implementation of this call is OPTIONAL. If not supported a 501 MUST be returned.</t>

<t anchor="_b8b53a46-044d-e1d8-fb97-83021748564a">Normative URI template of the asynchronous template revert end-point per <xref target="RFC6570" section="" relative=""></xref>:</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_1610ed1a-7cd3-ca2b-3685-1d2b8b28ed6b"><![CDATA[POST

{+urlAPI}/v2/domainTemplates/providers/{providerId}/services
/{serviceId}/revert{?domain,host,instanceId}]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_ec54aa60-8df3-19d0-65d1-b30589ddbdf5">This API allows the removal of a template from a user domain/host using an OAuth request.</t>

<t anchor="_e6a956e5-6182-ef52-5937-94f07e9882af">The provider and service name in the URL MUST match the values provided during authorization.</t>

<t anchor="_c044b004-0fd3-2f95-2789-2e01393bb6f4">This call MUST validate that the template exists and has been applied to the domain by the Service Provider, or an error response with code 410 SHOULD be returned that the call would have no effect.</t>

<t anchor="_7052b5d2-cfcb-6bc7-e779-582b3929513c">An example URL might look like:</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_adfe05a6-cd32-cf02-ed2b-444c7961d12f"><![CDATA[POST

https://connect.dnsprovider.example/v2/domainTemplates/providers
/exampleservice.example/services/template1/revert?domain=example.com]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_805943f6-bb47-83f7-3dce-0c59e77e3fe9">Allowed parameters:</t>

<table anchor="_9702b2db-f05c-2ff0-bf72-d243b3bc00c3"><name>URI template parameters of the revert end-point in the async flow</name><thead><tr><th align="left">Property</th><th align="left">Key</th><th align="left">Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><strong>URL API</strong></td><td align="left">urlAPI</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) Value of urlAPI from the settings endpoint.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Service Provider Id</strong></td><td align="left">providerId</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) identifier of the Service Provider of the template to be applied</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Service Id</strong></td><td align="left">serviceId</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) The name or identifier of the template to be applied.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Domain</strong></td><td align="left">domain</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) The Zone Apex domain name being configured. It MUST match the domain that was authorized in the token.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Host</strong></td><td align="left">host</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) The host name of the Sub Domain that was authorized in the token. If omitted or left blank, the template is being applied to the Zone Apex.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>InstanceId</strong></td><td align="left">instanceId</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) Only applicable to templates supporting multiple instances (see  <xref target="template-definition">multiInstance</xref> template property). For DNS Provider storing information about applied templates allows removal of single instance of template. If missing all instances of template MUST be removed.</td></tr></tbody></table>

<t anchor="_b5c69dc1-403c-b2e9-793e-bf80ca7a548d">The DNS Provider MUST be able to accept these on the query string or in the body of the POST with <tt>application/json</tt> encoding.</t>

<t anchor="_6550abcf-ef0c-9efa-f670-b816d7509650">Response codes Success, Authorization, and Errors are identical to above with the addition of the 501 code.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="_a6b8fd16-e571-d96b-98e7-6f90ef89fb7d"><name>OAuth Flow: Revoking access</name>

<t anchor="_b2098e14-a024-abcd-04a8-815f530bfda7">Like all OAuth flows, the user may revoke the access at any time using UX at the DNS Provider site. As such the Service Provider needs to be aware that their access to the API may be denied.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="verification-of-changes"><name>Verification of Changes</name>

<t anchor="_a38c7209-5a4e-00ad-b7e0-499f4b012620">There are circumstances where the Service Provider may wish to verify that the template was successfully applied. Without Domain Donnect, this typically involved the Service Provider querying DNS to see if the changes to DNS had been made.</t>

<t anchor="_d314e063-c95c-5db5-3aea-717a2cb4a735">This same technique works with Domain Connect, and if necessary can be triggered either manually on the Service Provider site or automatically upon page/window activation in the browser when the browser window for the DNS Provider is closed.</t>

<t anchor="_11881fd7-d778-e7d4-dd6e-1adb19f4fc0d">When the redirect_uri is used and an error is not present in the URI, the Service Provider can not assume the changes were applied to DNS. While true in most circumstances, users can tamper with or alter the return url in the browser. As such it is recommend that enablement of a service be based on verification of changes to DNS.</t>
</section>
</section>
    <section anchor="_1d6987ca-1f9b-4419-ebeb-7569f413e196"><name>Domain Connect Objects and Templates</name>

<section anchor="_1cb36f5f-775b-8114-8ded-0cb9e28fb568"><name>Template Versioning</name>

<t anchor="_86b03117-6267-90c1-ed62-8fd7cc7d5caa">If a breaking change is made to a template it is recommended that a new template be created. While on the surface versioning looks appealing, in reality this is rarely needed.</t>

<t anchor="_b4b82847-3b08-cc1b-3de9-1d8e4f6acb95">Any changes to the template need to account for existing users with settings in DNS, some applied through Domain Connect and some manual. So when changes are made, they are often backward compatible.</t>

<t anchor="_d0ca5ca4-7d40-568c-de6f-296563a574db">Note that when a template changes, it does need to be on-boarded with the DNS Providers.</t>

<t anchor="_550f3b40-8773-11ca-d5aa-38d939cfd98a">The <xref target="template-definition">version field</xref> of the template definition serves the purpose of transparency between the DNS Provider and the Service Provider in case of such changes.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="template-definition"><name>Template Definition</name>

<t anchor="_9c9c2855-ecd5-e591-dd6c-3e9db4f195ce">A template is defined as a standard JSON data structure containing the following data. Field values MUST be defined unless otherwise indicated.</t>

<table anchor="_ff9c2067-beae-12f8-ad6e-28627ef4ebd2"><name>properties of the template definition</name><thead><tr><th align="left">Data Element</th><th align="left">Type</th><th align="left">Key</th><th align="left">Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><strong>Service Provider Id</strong></td><td align="left">String</td><td align="left">providerId</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) The unique identifier of the Service Provider that created this template. This is used in the URLs to identify the Service Provider. To ensure non-coordinated uniqueness, this SHOULD be the domain name of the Service Provider (e.g. exampleservice.example).</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Service Provider Name</strong></td><td align="left">String</td><td align="left">providerName</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) The name of the Service Provider suitable for display. This SHOULD be displayed to the user on the DNS Provider consent UX.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Service Id</strong></td><td align="left">String</td><td align="left">serviceId</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) The name or identifier of the template. This is used in URLs to identify the template. It is also used in the scope parameter for OAuth. It MUST NOT contain space characters, and SHOULD be URL friendly.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Service Name</strong></td><td align="left">String</td><td align="left">serviceName</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) The name of the service suitable for display to the user. This SHOULD be displayed to the user on the DNS Provider consent UX.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Version</strong></td><td align="left">Integer</td><td align="left">version</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) If present this represents a version of the template and SHOULD be changed with each update of the template content. This opaque value is mainly informational to improve communication and transparency between providers.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Logo</strong></td><td align="left">String</td><td align="left">logoUrl</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) A graphical logo representing the Service Provider and/or Service for use in any web-based flow. If present this MAY be displayed to the user on the DNS Provider consent UX.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Description</strong></td><td align="left">Text</td><td align="left">description</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) A textual description of what this template attempts to do. This is meant to assist developers and MUST NOT be displayed to the user.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Variable Description</strong></td><td align="left">Text</td><td align="left">variableDescription</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) A textual description of what the variables are. This is meant to assist developers and MUST NOT be displayed to the user.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Synchronous Block</strong></td><td align="left">Boolean</td><td align="left">syncBlock</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) Indicates that the synchronous protocol MUST be disabled for this template. The default for this is false.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Shared</strong></td><td align="left">Boolean</td><td align="left">shared</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) This flag has been deprecated. It used to indicate that the template allowed a dynamic  <tt>providerName</tt> on the query string. It is replaced with the <tt>sharedProviderName</tt> flag in v2.2 of the spec.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Shared Provider Name</strong></td><td align="left">Boolean</td><td align="left">sharedProviderName</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) This flag indicates that the template allows the caller to pass in additional information for the  <tt>providerName</tt>. This information SHOULD augment the display of the <tt>providerName</tt> from the template. The default for this is false. For backward compatability with DNS Providers not at V2.2 of the spec it is recommended that the shared flag also be set.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Shared Service Name</strong></td><td align="left">Boolean</td><td align="left">sharedServiceName</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) This flag indicates that the template allows the caller to pass in additional information for the  <tt>serviceName</tt>. This information SHOULD augment the display of the <tt>serviceName</tt> from the template. The default for this is false.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Synchronous Public Key Domain</strong></td><td align="left">String</td><td align="left">syncPubKeyDomain</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) When present, indicates that calls to apply a template synchronously MUST be digitally signed. The value indicates the domain name for querying the TXT record from DNS that contains the public key used for signing.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Synchronous Redirect Domains</strong></td><td align="left">String</td><td align="left">syncRedirectDomain</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) When present, this is a comma separated list of domain names for which redirects are allowed be sent to after applying a template for the synchronous flow. DNS Provider MUST NOT send redirects to any other domain name not included on this list.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Multiple Instance</strong></td><td align="left">Boolean</td><td align="left">multiInstance</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) Defaults to False. When set to True, it indicates that the template MAY be applied multiple times. This only impacts DNS Providers that maintain template state in DNS.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Warn Phishing</strong></td><td align="left">Boolean</td><td align="left">warnPhishing</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) When present, this tells the DNS Provider that the template likely contains variables susceptible to phishing attacks and the provider is unable to digitally sign the requests. When set the DNS Provider SHOULD display warnings to the user and be more verbose about the changes applied. The default value for this is false.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Host Required</strong></td><td align="left">Boolean</td><td align="left">hostRequired</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) Defaults to false. When present this indicates that the template has been authored to work only when both domain and host are provided. An example where this would be true would be a template where CNAME is set on the fully qualified domain name. This is largely informational, as most DNS Providers already enforce such rules on the DNS level anyway.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Template Records</strong></td><td align="left">Array of Template Records</td><td align="left">records</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) A list of records for the template.</td></tr></tbody></table>
</section>

<section anchor="template-record"><name>Template Record</name>

<t anchor="_6a3c5ce8-349b-c941-a93c-31d69ae2d4d7">Each template record is an entry that contains a type and several other values depending on the type.</t>

<t anchor="_40ff60da-2028-77ea-7891-d592c374597d">Many of these values can contain variables, which are expressed as strings surrounded with "%" or special variable "@" (See: <xref target="variables"></xref>). Variables are replaced with values when the template is applied.</t>

<t anchor="_aaec417b-1af7-a220-4378-8c2e2305230f">It is noted that as a best practice the variable portions SHOULD be constrained to as small as possible a portion of the resulting DNS record.</t>

<t anchor="_56830184-a567-5faf-4207-8eb50174856e">For example, say a Service Provider requires a CNAME of one of three values for their users: s01.example.com, s02.example.com, and s03.example.com.</t>

<t anchor="_43414223-eb5b-de72-ff9b-32bb775484cb">The value in the template could simply contain <tt>%servercluster%</tt>, and the fully qualified string passed in. Alternatively, the value in the template could contain  <tt>%var%.example.com</tt> and a value of <tt>01</tt>, <tt>02</tt>, or <tt>03</tt> passed in. By placing more fixed data into the template, the template is more secure.</t>

<t anchor="_90884201-7116-5704-1b7e-388af51db5c1">Each record MUST contain the following elements unless otherwise specified.</t>

<table anchor="_fa7a329e-4580-f5c4-8339-f901f5b76ddf"><name>properties of the template record definition</name><thead><tr><th align="left">Data Element</th><th align="left">Type</th><th align="left">Key</th><th align="left">Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><strong>Type</strong></td><td align="left">enum</td><td align="left">type</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) Describes the type of record in DNS, or the operation impacting DNS.<br />  Valid values include: A, AAAA, CNAME, MX, TXT, SRV, or SPFM.<br /> The DNS Provider MUST support the core set of records A, AAAA, CNAME, MX, TXT, SRV.<br /> The DNS Provider SHOULD support SPFM record for high interoperability with existing templates<br /> <br /> All other record types MAY be specified by type name as listed in IANA registry for DNS Resource Record (RR) TYPEs. Unknown record types MAY be specified as per  <xref target="RFC3597" section="" relative=""></xref> by the word "TYPE" immediately followed by the decimal RR type number, with no intervening whitespace. Support for other record types is OPTIONAL.<br />  For each type, additional fields would be REQUIRED.<br /> * A: host, pointsTo, TTL<br /> * AAAA: host, pointsTo, TTL<br /> * CNAME: host, pointsTo, TTL (host MUST NOT be null or @ unless  <tt>hostRequired</tt> is defined <tt>true</tt> for the template)<br /> * NS: host, pointsTo, TTL (host MUST NOT be null or @ unless  <tt>hostRequired</tt> is defined <tt>true</tt> for the template)<br /> * TXT: host, data, TTL, txtConflict-MatchingMode, txtConflict-MatchingPrefix<br /> * MX: host, pointsTo, TTL, priority<br /> * SRV: name, target, TTL, priority, protocol, service, weight, port<br /> * SPFM: host, spfRules<br /> * other record types: host, data, TTL<br /></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Group Id</strong></td><td align="left">String</td><td align="left">groupId</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) This parameter identifies the group the record belongs to when applying changes. This MUST NOT contain variables.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Essential</strong></td><td align="left">enum</td><td align="left">essential</td><td align="left">(OPTIONAL) This parameter indicates how the record is treated during conflict detection with existing templates.<br />  If the DNS Provider is not implementing applied template state in DNS this is ignored.<br />  Always (default) - record MUST be applied and kept with the template<br />  OnApply - record MUST be applied but can be later removed without dropping the whole template<br /></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Host</strong></td><td align="left">String</td><td align="left">host</td><td align="left">(REQUIRED) The host for A, AAAA, CNAME, NS, TXT, MX and other unspecified record type values.<br />  This value is relative to the applied host and domain, unless trailed by a ".".<br />  A value of empty or  <tt>@</tt> indicates the root of the applied host and domain. In other words <tt>"[host.]example.com."</tt>.<br />  This value SHOULD NOT contain variables unless absolutely necessary. This is discussed below.<br /></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Name</strong></td><td align="left">String</td><td align="left">name</td><td align="left">The name for the SRV record.<br />  This value is relative to the applied host and domain. A value of empty or  <tt>@</tt> indicates the root of the applied host and domain.<br />  This value SHOULD NOT contain variables unless absolutely necessary. This is discussed below.<br /></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Points To</strong></td><td align="left">String</td><td align="left">pointsTo</td><td align="left">The pointsTo location for A, AAAA, CNAME, NS and MX records.<br />  A value of empty or @ indicates the host and domain name being applied or [host.]example.com<br /></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>TTL</strong></td><td align="left">Int or string repr. of Int</td><td align="left">ttl</td><td align="left">The time-to-live for the record in DNS. Valid for A, AAAA, CNAME, NS, TXT, MX, and SRV records. In order to avoid operational unpredactibility of the template and the challenges outlined below this SHOULD NOT contain variables unless absolutely necessary. If it does, the variable MUST be included as string in the template definition to build a valid JSON and the variable MUST be the only value content. Prefixes, suffixes or multiple variables MUST NOT be used.  This value, no matter if variable or constant, is understood as "best effort" by DNS Provider and MAY be limited or adjusted by local policy at runtime or during template onboarding, like applying a certain minimum or maximum value of TTL or an enumeration of TTL values supported by the DNS Provider. The DNS Provider SHOULD NOT reject template application because of invalid value, rather pick the nearest supported value or a default, in order to avoid necessity of per provider adjustment to the application flow.  Support of variables in this field is OPTIONAL for DNS Provider.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Data</strong></td><td align="left">String</td><td align="left">data</td><td align="left">The data for a TXT record in DNS. A value of empty or @ indicates the host and domain name being applied or [host.]example.com  For any unspecified record type this field contains the canonical presentation format of the given record. The representation SHALL follow  <xref target="RFC3597" section="" relative=""></xref> as generic or type-specific encoding. This MUST NOT be used for any record type explicitly listed in the Type field with specific data fields.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>TXT Conflict Matching Mode</strong></td><td align="left">String</td><td align="left">txtConflictMatchingMode</td><td align="left">Describes how conflicts on the TXT record are detected. Possible values are None, All, or Prefix. The default value is None.  <xref target="record-types-conflicts">See below</xref>.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>TXT Conflict Matching Prefix</strong></td><td align="left">String</td><td align="left">txtConflictMatchingPrefix</td><td align="left">The prefix to detect conflicts when txtConflict-MatchingMode is "Prefix". This MUST NOT contain variables.  <xref target="record-types-conflicts">See below</xref>.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Priority</strong></td><td align="left">Int or string repr. of Int</td><td align="left">priority</td><td align="left">The priority for an MX or SRV record. This MAY contain variable but if it does the variable MUST be included as string in the template definition to build a valid JSON and the variable MUST be the only content of the value field. Prefixes, suffixes or multiple variables MUST NOT be used.  Support of variables in this field is OPTIONAL for DNS Provider.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Weight</strong></td><td align="left">Int or string repr. of Int</td><td align="left">weight</td><td align="left">The weight for the SRV record. This MAY contain variable but if it does the variable MUST be included as string in the template definition to build a valid JSON and the variable MUST be the only content of the value field. Prefixes, suffixes or multiple variables MUST NOT be used.  Support of variables in this field is OPTIONAL for DNS Provider.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Port</strong></td><td align="left">Int or string repr. of Int</td><td align="left">port</td><td align="left">The port for the SRV record. This MAY contain variable but if it does the variable MUST be included as string in the template definition to build a valid JSON and the variable MUST be the only content of the value field. Prefixes, suffixes or multiple variables MUST NOT be used.  Support of variables in this field is OPTIONAL for DNS Provider.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Protocol</strong></td><td align="left">String</td><td align="left">protocol</td><td align="left">The protocol for the SRV record.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Service</strong></td><td align="left">String</td><td align="left">service</td><td align="left">The symbolic name for the SRV record.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>Target</strong></td><td align="left">String</td><td align="left">target</td><td align="left">The target for the SRV record.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><strong>SPF Rules</strong></td><td align="left">String</td><td align="left">spfRules</td><td align="left">These are desired rules for the SPF TXT record. These rules SHOULD be merged with other SPFM records into final SPF TXT record. See <xref target="spf-record-merging"></xref>.</td></tr></tbody></table>
</section>
</section>
    <section anchor="_fd2ff659-f521-b622-9371-dc5ef6cd89ae"><name>Template Considerations</name>

<section anchor="_fb608f02-1523-7131-f791-469ba5cc600e"><name>Template State in DNS</name>

<t anchor="_07b8b402-4157-4eb4-e916-8cc89e97de30">DNS Providers may choose to maintain state inside records in DNS indicating the templates writing the records.</t>

<t anchor="_59078bac-73c5-fc16-8957-2855a7d5c0d7">A DNS Provider that maintains this state may be able to provide an improved experience for users, telling them the services enabled. They also may be able to have more advanced handling of conflicts.</t>

<t anchor="_a1ecd250-1f34-40b7-54c1-d1e72666c5db">To make the implementation burden reasonable for DNS Providers, Domain Connect does not dictate the approach.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="_8900963d-b390-f69b-f986-192b45224eb9"><name>Disclosure of Changes and Conflicts</name>

<t anchor="_443bb5c4-db6c-9a50-59af-89771dbafa21">It is left to the discretion of the DNS Provider to determine what is disclosed to the user when granting permission and/or applying changes to DNS. This includes disclosing the records being applied and the records that may be overwritten.</t>

<t anchor="_4f33f9ee-91c1-2550-c5ce-92c32b0efb56">For changes being made, one DNS Provider may decide to simply tell the user the name of the service being enabled. Another may decide to display the records being set. And another may progressively display both.</t>

<t anchor="_4a18df9f-e1ce-8836-fc4e-dc1055f8bdb5">For conflict detection, one DNS Provider may simply overwrite changed records without warning. Another may detect conflicts and warn the user of the records that will change. And another may implement logic to further detect, warn, and remove any of the existing templates that overlap with the new template once applied (this assumes they are a DNS Provider that maintains template state in DNS).</t>

<t anchor="_a9748daf-7a54-1272-1b20-d93c3c1742b2">As an example, consider applying a template that sets two records (recordA and recordB) into a zone. Next consider applying a second template that overlaps with the first template (recordB and recordC). If the DNS maintains template state and removes conflicting templates, applying the second template would remove the first template. Application of the second template would conflict with recordB and the entire first template would be removed.</t>

<t anchor="_5c5c17aa-e0e0-59c2-28ea-5d46b7ee2fa6">Manual changes made by the user at the DNS Provider may also have appropriate warnings in place to prevent unwanted changes; with overrides being possible and removal of conflicting templates.</t>

<t anchor="_33bf36bb-2b97-a5dd-e391-8e4122c5dc1a">For the synchronous flow, this happens while the user is present.</t>

<t anchor="_6dd75643-002d-bd54-36a4-e20cedc41cee">For the asynchronous flow, the consent UX is similar. However, the changes are made later using the API and OAuth. The DNS Provider MAY decide to detect conflicts and return these from the API without applying the change using the proper response code. If the force parameter is set, the changes MUST be applied regardless of conflicts.</t>

<t anchor="_42c6453c-3c1c-8870-df96-47e472c6400e">It is ultimately left to the DNS Provider to determine the amount of disclosure and/or conflict detection. The only requirement is that after a template is applied the new records MUST be applied in totality.</t>

<t anchor="_415cb23e-70b2-378a-25a1-700c314c2c7b">A reasonable set of recommendations for the UX might consist of:</t>

<ul anchor="_fae8304c-40b5-e9ce-6dbc-26160d7271b0"><li>The consent UX SHOULD inform the user of the service that will be enabled. If the user want to know the specifics, the DNS Provider could provide a "show details" link to the user. This could display to them the specific records that are being set in DNS.</li>
<li>If there are conflicts, either at the template or record level, the consent UX SHOULD warn the user about these conflicts. For templates, this would be services that would be disabled. For records, this would be records that would be deleted or overwritten. This could be progressively disclosed.</li>
</ul>
</section>

<section anchor="record-types-conflicts"><name>Record Types and Conflicts</name>

<t anchor="_f21f052a-1f4c-7fca-049d-64fc3a5003bc">Conflict detection done by the DNS Provider prior to template application has to take into consideration specifics of each DNS record type. The rules outlined below ensure predictable conflict resolution between DNS Providers. Each rule applies to the records on the very same host, unless specifed otherwise.</t>

<ul anchor="_242bba56-df5b-b512-741f-0d903bf0109e"><li>CNAME record conflicts with TXT, MX, AAAA, A and existing CNAME records, and any other records of these types conflict with an existing CNAME record. Note: CNAME records cannot be at the root of the zone.</li>
<li>NS records conflict with all other records. This includes of the same host, and for any record ending with the NS host. For example, an NS record of foo will conflict with any foo, <tt>www.foo</tt>, <tt>bar.foo</tt>, etc. Similarly all other record type conflict with NS records in the same manner.</li>
<li>MX, SRV records always conflict with records of the same type</li>
<li>A and AAAA records conflict with any other A and/or AAAA record, to avoid IPv4 and IPv6 pointing to different services.</li>
<li><t anchor="_720711cb-1011-60c0-085c-f4a8fb35514a">TXT records conflict detection is handled looking at txtConflictMatchingMode parameter</t>
<ul anchor="_006d9c8e-8d18-e854-7383-16cda7ca8ea9"><li>None: This indicates that the TXT records do not conflict with any other TXT record. This is the default setting, if not specified.</li>
<li>All: This indicates that the TXT records conflict with any other TXT record</li>
<li>Prefix: This indicates that TXT record conflict with any other TXT containing value starting with txtConflictMatchingPrefix</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</section>

<section anchor="_d5d735a3-be45-8c48-0ed2-b82cae13daef"><name>Apply, Re-apply, and Multi-Instance</name>

<t anchor="_d671235e-f486-08dd-2232-8346150d31ca">There is an additional consideration for DNS Providers that maintain the state of an applied template when re-applying a template.</t>

<t anchor="_470a4f96-a649-c6f8-9ae3-f8ec9c14bfba">To avoid unnecessary conflict warnings to the user, under normal use when re-applying a template such a DNS Provider SHOULD remove the previously applied template on the same host.</t>

<t anchor="_544f9cd8-7f36-6651-0f2f-7cef475fb50b">This may not be desireable for all templates, as a limited set of templates are designed to be applied multiple times. To faciliate this the template can have the flag <xref target="template-definition">multiInstance</xref> set. This tells the DNS Provider that the template is expected to be written multiple times and that a re-apply MUST NOT remove previous instances.</t>

<t anchor="_2dfd1a00-e4df-06a9-f45a-e8a918b1c043">This setting only impacts DNS Providers that maintain applied template state. DNS Providers that do not maintain applied template state can only rely on the normal conflict resolution rules, and this flag has no impact.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="non-essential-record"><name>Non-essential records</name>

<t anchor="_fb9f8582-4fed-ca0f-3511-714bf87314da">Typically a template specifies a list of DNS records which are required for the service. There may be cases where some records are only required for a very short period of time, and removing or altering the record later (either by the end user or through application of another template) should not trigger conflict detection.</t>

<t anchor="_c02d2dbe-f198-e02b-705d-d3c93eaebc3a">This can be controlled by the <xref target="template-record">essential</xref> property of a record in the template.</t>

<t anchor="_8812fdd5-a86f-79d5-aaae-e51e15809976">Again, this setting only impacts DNS Providers that maintain applied template state.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="_c61dd75b-d707-76b3-2632-392da3bd4e97"><name>Template Scope</name>

<t anchor="_d701be4a-ffa7-26d9-0c37-0af38cda59cb">For DNS Providers that maintain template state, an individual template is scoped to the set of records applied to a fully qualified domain. This includes the Zone Apex and the host (aka Sub Domain) at apply time.</t>

<t anchor="_14fb9739-ebe9-64d6-3ab4-cdd6b0bbde44">As an example, if a template is applied on <tt>domain=example.com&#x26;host=sub1</tt> a later application of the template on <tt>domain=example.com&#x26;host=sub2</tt> must be treated as a distinct template. If a conflict is detected later with the records set into <tt>"sub2.example.com"</tt>, only the records set with this template would be removed.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="_d4f1776c-136a-be38-be6c-fcea2981a4dc"><name>Host/Name in Template</name>

<t anchor="_087ef81d-34cc-7dc1-75d3-fcab7143bd51">Template records contain the host name of the record to set into the zone (called name for SRV records). This value MUST be considered relative to the domain/host when the template is applied, unless followed by a trailing ".".</t>

<t anchor="_d1638878-46cc-d99c-3654-9b8527824073">Consider a template record of type A with a host value of "xyz". When the template is applied to a domain=example.com and an empty host value, the resulting zone after the template is applied will contain an A record of "xyz" (or "xyz.example.com." as absolute domain name in DNS master file notation).</t>

<t anchor="_e5cb9eb0-639f-325e-5748-5734943f841c">If the same template is applied to a domain=example.com and host=bar, the zone will contain an A record of "xyz.bar" (or "xyz.bar.example.com." as absolute domain name).</t>

<t anchor="_d2a4ec54-9791-02ec-94c0-6ac72f416733">A value of @ for host in the template is a placeholder for an empty value. In other words @ would point to "bar.example.com." when the same template is applied to domain=example.com and host=bar.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="_e795fd8c-b612-64f0-114c-31f1da1c9410"><name>PointsTo in Template</name>

<t anchor="_b6d62496-67d9-7255-838b-02953e2d999c">Template records of certain types contain the <tt>pointsTo</tt> value to set in the zone. For record types such as <tt>CNAME</tt> where this can be a fully qualified domain name.</t>

<t anchor="_87493741-2d4c-8b7e-7bf5-9bdf3624f02e">A value of <tt>@</tt> in <tt>pointsTo</tt> field in the template is a shortcut for the fully qualified domain name of the domain/host being applied.</t>

<t anchor="_4b91e09d-7bee-4747-71fd-33f0d877fc5a">Consider a template record of type <tt>CNAME</tt> with a <tt>pointsTo</tt> value of <tt>"@"</tt>. After a template of <tt>domain=example.com</tt> and an empty host is applied, the <tt>pointsTo</tt> value (or corresponding field) in the resulting zone would be <tt>"example.com"</tt>. After a template of <tt>domain=example.com</tt> with <tt>host=bar</tt> is applied, the points to value would be <tt>"bar.example.com"</tt>.</t>

<t anchor="_3768c1c8-fa1e-2a51-259e-92b3af1309eb">Any domain in a <tt>pointsTo</tt> field in a template MUST be considered fully qualified and not relative.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="variables"><name>Variables</name>

<section anchor="_3f9de739-48ec-a3dc-8027-1ad73c70484c"><name>Variable Syntax</name>

<t anchor="_b77629a3-2f39-9406-045b-ab1c1c3474d6">Variable expressions are the parameterized parts of a Domain Connect Template. Each expression contains one variable specifier (which can be either a named variable or a special variable "@") that is replaced with a value during template application.</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_15123266-6b58-fe74-934d-d65a7dcbf179" type="abnf"><![CDATA[     variable-expression    =  named-variable / template-apex-var
     named-variable         = "%" variable-name "%"
     template-apex-var      = "@"
     variable-name          =  1*(ALPHA / DIGIT / "-" / "_" )]]></sourcecode>

</section>

<section anchor="_5585aafd-9d4b-153b-01cd-e5439a9707d6"><name>Special and Built-In Variables</name>

<t anchor="_9c5c2fae-cdf3-1cbc-c69c-820585fab34e">There are three Built-In variables:</t>

<ul anchor="_52ada67f-6478-db9a-a107-24fa0f35cac5"><li>%host%: This is the host passed from the query string</li>
<li>%domain%: This is the domain passed from the query string</li>
<li>%fqdn%: This is the fully qualified domain name or template application e.g. [host.]domain</li>
</ul>

<t anchor="_92af2a47-43d0-44bb-e151-3fc436215419">For example, with the query string "domain=example.com&#x26;host=", %fqdn% in a template would be "example.com", and with "domain=example.com&#x26;host=sub1", %fqdn% in a template would be "sub1.example.com".</t>

<t anchor="_6708cea3-d114-61f7-0b27-735a373fa7e9">The @ variable has special meaning, and can be used in the host/name field or in the pointsTo/data field in isolation.</t>

<t anchor="_c88a08c5-5e7d-848a-e285-edc11dd0a277">For the host/name field it is a shortcut for the value "%fqdn%.". The trailing dot here is equal to the DNS master file notation <xref target="RFC1035" section="" relative=""></xref>, which indicates the value is absolute. Without the trailing ".", the value in this field is relative to the [host.]example.com value.</t>

<t anchor="_f33341c5-36ed-b291-55b4-91834474a6bb">For the pointsTo/data field it is a shortcut for for the "%fqdn%". The pointsTo and data files are always absolute for these fields.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="_98e877fa-72fe-2ca6-4ef5-5afd147153c5"><name>Variable substitution</name>

<section anchor="_d9a2249f-b490-b3db-5648-85e46d3ad08b"><name>Input Values</name>

<t anchor="_7d379db1-845d-286f-d4a6-cf372d2ba548">Input values for variable substitution MUST be treated as strings.  While the underlying data source (e.g., query string, JSON string) might represent values in different data types, the Domain Connect protocol mandates that these values are interpreted and substituted as strings within the templates.</t>

<t anchor="_66afbeec-01e0-afa9-5a1b-0bb251d978f9">If the data source requires encoding of certain characters (e.g., special characters, spaces), the DNS Provider implementation MUST handle decoding of the value before variable substitution. The resulting substituted value MUST reflect the exact original input value string.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="_54dbb42a-db64-ef8a-b337-e61a1ee09ba2"><name>Processing</name>

<t anchor="_69925676-e604-57f3-6911-57f77b879e12">When a template is applied, the variables in the template are replaced with the values passed as input.</t>

<t anchor="_7f72c8f7-4430-2467-c8b3-007175aa9761">Variables are only allowed in template fields of type string, therefore the input field values from the template MUST be decoded from JSON string encoding before variable substitution.</t>

<t anchor="_35786a59-b9c2-9473-61bb-839bbe96e08e">Variables are replaced in the template fields in the order they are found. If a variable is not found in the input, the processing MUST fail. After a variable is replaced, only the remaining string is used for further variable substitution.</t>

<t anchor="_5fb4a30a-1cc3-72ca-03ef-5d0867ff767c">The result of the processing MAY still contain variable expressions coming from Input Values of variable substitution. The processing MUST NOT fail in this case, and the variable expressions MUST be left as is.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="variables-and-hosts"><name>Variables and Host/Name in Template</name>

<t anchor="_e8211caf-25f7-0ba1-911a-764001a9d1de">While templates do allow for variables in a host or name field values, these SHOULD be used very sparingly.</t>

<t anchor="_fd901d70-251d-0df4-221b-9ac0bbd169eb">As an example, consider setting up hosting for a site. But instead of applying the template to a domain/host, the name of the host is placed as a variable in the template.</t>

<t anchor="_1dfa5a86-040e-fde5-9ad3-0377a27563a3">Such a template might contain an A record of the form:</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_4be6c24f-f614-198a-495a-353751974b9d" type="json"><![CDATA[{
    "type": "A",
    "host": "%var%",
    "pointsTo": "192.0.2.2",
    "ttl": 1800
}]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_9dc2f6cc-9540-63fd-f91a-5ad5862fe32f">This template could be applied on a domain like example.com with the var set to <tt>"sub"</tt>, <tt>"sub1"</tt>, <tt>"sub2"</tt>, etc.</t>

<t anchor="_47a9e631-c905-16bd-e65e-051b4cb49846">Application of this template would be at the domain level for <tt>"example.com"</tt>. This causes problems for application/re-application of the template, conflict detection, and template removal.</t>

<t anchor="_a611d8b2-e793-4a1c-8129-78a1bec26135">Since this template would be applied to the domain only, DNS Providers that maintain template state would remove previous instances of the template before re-application. This means applying this template with  <tt>var=sub</tt> would result in the A record for sub.example.com to be set to the value <tt>192.0.2.2</tt>. Later, applying the template on "example.com" with the <tt>var=sub2</tt> should remove the old template before setting the new one. <tt>sub.example.com</tt> would be removed, and <tt>sub2.example.com</tt> would be set to the value <tt>192.0.2.2</tt>.</t>

<t anchor="_2ecc1d4f-2f5c-46ad-5e78-ea33b3f2a757">Furthermore, determining conflicts would be impossible when the user is granting consent for asynchronous operations (OAuth). This is because the host would be indeterminate.</t>

<t anchor="_f47c0735-6ee7-6059-d1d2-95678cf61ac4">To solve this problem, templates MUST be considered as scoped to a <tt>domain</tt> and a <tt>host</tt> value. For synchronous operations, the <tt>host</tt> value is specified in the url. For asynchronous operations, permissions are granted for specific  <tt>host</tt> values, whose value is later specified when applying the template.</t>

<t anchor="_96bf294e-1c90-798d-f887-5030d1078ec0">Some templates might want to utilize CNAME or TXT records with host values containing some form of user identification for validation of domain ownership, and these are often passed in variables. In those cases usage of variables in <tt>host</tt> field value can be applied without risk of issues mentioned above. In all other cases it is RECOMMENDED not to define variables in the <tt>host</tt> field.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="_d2dcb2a2-d9fc-f0f9-445a-c0e8dd0a8bba"><name>Variables and Security</name>

<t anchor="_577db6ef-c7f7-a8ff-d286-a8113afb4d60">As discussed, with variables consideration is necessary to prevent certain styles of phishing attacks.</t>

<t anchor="_7c52af8a-31ed-a181-ecc6-16c0706a8cc2">The more static the value in the template record, the more secure the template. When static values are not possible, a carefully crafted link could hijack DNS settings.</t>

<t anchor="_3d34f418-c5e2-518f-eb31-6beac2e0d0fe">Mitigations to this are discussed above.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="_28703502-9d1d-b5ea-f11d-fca388875992"><name>Variable Examples</name>

<t anchor="_ed1f431d-0370-47f2-b919-ff1415c29c5b">Example template:</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_089d79e1-e8e1-7429-abea-fc8ec64a3e62" type="json"><![CDATA[[{
    "type": "CNAME",
    "host": "www",
    "pointsTo": "@",
    "ttl": 1800
},
{
    "type": "A",
    "host": "@",
    "pointsTo": "192.0.2.1",
    "ttl": 1800
}]]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_6e54f692-6452-9f66-196c-09a411390f8d">Template applied with <tt>domain=example.com</tt> and <tt>host</tt> parameter missing or empty:</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_4d01d59a-c103-aa55-da90-8ffb18160044"><![CDATA[www 1800 IN CNAME example.com.
@   1800 IN A 192.0.2.1]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_97021c11-bf43-b265-268d-27a096fd4ad9"><em>alternatively</em></t>

<sourcecode anchor="_e4d0bcb5-069e-4f8a-27b1-cc7010a2b861"><![CDATA[www.example.com.    1800 IN CNAME example.com.
example.com.        1800 IN A 192.0.2.1]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_b79f5dd9-5a9f-0dec-8b66-85120a185587">Template applied with <tt>domain=example.com</tt> and <tt>host=bar</tt>:</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_d5ecdebe-debb-c383-58d4-6ab154800bec"><![CDATA[www.bar 1800 IN CNAME bar.example.com.
bar     1800 IN A 192.0.2.1]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_f088b85f-a22c-791b-83ba-731bb3160558">alternatively</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_395f5e7e-89c4-3e74-4f50-fe97367aefec"><![CDATA[www.bar.example.com.    1800 IN CNAME bar.example.com.
bar.example.com.        1800 IN A 192.0.2.1]]></sourcecode>

</section>
</section>

<section anchor="spf-record-merging"><name>SPF TXT Record</name>

<section anchor="_0dd6b6b3-da60-b5bd-aee2-91a7da9506fa"><name>What is SPF?</name>

<t anchor="_1e8ee3d6-aa89-78ee-c6f2-5cf65bd54837">SPF stands for Sender Policy Framework specified in <xref target="RFC7208" section="" relative=""></xref>. It is a record that specifies a list of authorized host names and/or IP addresses from which mail can originate from for a given domain name.</t>

<t anchor="_fb58cb04-a05c-fd7f-5a05-4e62bf46e018">It manifests itself as a TXT record.  The format of which starts with v=spf1 followed by a list of "rules" of what to include/exclude.  If a rule passes, the mail is allowed. If it fails, it moves to the next rule. Typical record might appear as:</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_aef224a7-4bc3-8695-0903-5d89ea4b1d46"><![CDATA[v=spf1 include:policy.exampleprovider.example -all]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_daceb1a0-36cd-fb3a-a534-3ffe1875be48">This is an SPF record with two rules.  The first rule indicates that the rules for SPF record <tt>_policy.exampleprovider.example</tt> be included in this record. The second rule is a catch all (<tt>all</tt>). The default modifier for a rule is <tt>pass</tt> (+). Other modifiers are <tt>hard failure</tt> (<tt>-</tt>), <tt>soft failure</tt> (<tt>~</tt>) and <tt>neutral</tt> (<tt>?</tt>).</t>

<t anchor="_d30a5ee1-619b-28c6-2f7f-5d2d0038deb4">Note: A failure in SPF doesn't mean delivery won't happen, however depending on the policies of the receiving system, messages classified with <tt>hard failure</tt> or <tt>soft failure</tt> may not be delivered or marked as spam.</t>

<t anchor="_577dd4f7-d206-54ab-b51d-4302009b432a">The use of "all" at the end  is pretty common, although some providers mark it as <tt>~</tt> (soft fail) or <tt>?</tt> (neutral). The reality is that a good SPF record is tuned based on what services are attached to a domain. Not just one individual service.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="multiple-services"><name>Multiple Services</name>

<t anchor="_67c24ee1-ccf3-7a8a-b8ec-121e519ac7e5">If only one email sending service were active, the SPF record recommended by the provider is sufficient. But mail from a domain can often come from several different services.</t>

<t anchor="_2625a145-2b1e-fd69-513f-9ffcccf7508a">A very typical use case might be end user mail and an email newsletter service. Let's look at the SPF records recommended for individual services.</t>

<t anchor="_1db6c9c4-82be-9080-cbf1-581f3777d7ad">Mailer1: v=spf1 include:spf.mailer1.example -all Newsletter1: v=spf1 include:_spf.newsletter.example ~all</t>

<t anchor="_62621dfa-02d6-3b7b-1061-19107c40f919">All of these examples use the include syntax. This is fairly common. The use of all at the end is common, although is often inconsistent with the modifier.</t>

<t anchor="_1a707507-44eb-3fb3-fbc0-e2d3d72041ad">If a user installed Mailer1 and Newsletter1, their combined SPF record ought to be something like:</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_04ab4b78-b29a-064e-f735-7a2bee79400a"><![CDATA[v=spf1 include:spf.mailer1.example include:_spf.newsletter.example
 ~all]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_819d9476-0139-8cbf-cbfe-a9f8bfc2050c">We combined the two rules, and in this case picked the least restrictive all modifier.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="_9155d37b-4e9e-4876-fdff-73798bae8434"><name>SPF Record Merging</name>

<t anchor="_a6be59e0-b427-aa2d-2f98-9dc6353901fc">The challenge with SPF records and Domain Connect is that an individual service might recommend an SPF record. If only one service were active, this would be accurate. But with several services together only the DNS Provider is able to determine the valid shape of a SPF TXT record.</t>

<t anchor="_94356b8b-2511-5e3c-7db3-f3d4fb97a01d">One solution to this problem is to merge all related records. At the highest level, this means taking everything between the "v=spf1" and the "all" from each of the records and merging them together, terminating with hard-coded modifier on <tt>all</tt> at the end.  For an SPF record to fulfill it's purpose of protection against malicious email delivery, Domain Connect advises a fixed modifier <tt>"~"</tt> advising lower rating of the messages from other sources not specified in SPF. This setup offers a reasonable level of protection of mail delivery, on the other side does not reject the message in case forwarding facility is in place.</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_adf5c709-e862-c211-c65a-6b866d163d9e"><![CDATA[@ TXT v=spf1 include:spf.mailer1.example include:_spf.newsletter.exam
ple ~all]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_625d083e-e4bd-d8a9-4fec-00b50018c816">The other would be to write intermediate records, and reference these locally.</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_849d61c3-3563-9d76-070b-aa9a546b06f5"><![CDATA[r1.example.com. TXT v=spf1 include:spf.mailer1.example ~all
r2.example.com. TXT v=spf1 include:_spf.newsletter.example ~all
@ TXT v=spf1 include:r1.example.com include:r2.example.com ~all]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_3722e180-a9cc-d4f0-ca8f-44d4e3a70ba2">There are advantages and disadvantages to both approaches.  SPF records have a limit of 10 DNS lookups and record length is limited to 255 characters.  So depending on the embedded records both approaches might have advantages.</t>

<t anchor="_4516e55f-a18b-9a2e-2be8-5dbd6f0e4779">The implementation would be left to the DNS Provider, but to facilitate this SPF records SHOULD NOT be included in templates.  Instead, a new pseudo-record type is introduced in the template called <tt>SPFM</tt>. This has the following attribute:</t>

<dl anchor="_8c3dd0d3-5d4e-1a48-49ec-8ddba2740424"><dt>spfRules:</dt><dd anchor="_0957f4e3-2f23-3d61-4f6e-2236f848dde2"><t anchor="_0a6c201f-548a-b56b-4dec-546de2365fac">Determines the desired rules, basically everything but leading "v=spf1" and trailing <tt>all</tt> rule -  see: <xref target="template-record">SPF Rules</xref></t>
</dd></dl>

<t anchor="_0c198687-5c32-0e64-5793-3f3c1e815405">When a template is added or removed with an <tt>SPFM</tt> record in the template, some code would need to take the aggregate value of all <tt>SPFM</tt> records in all templates applied as well as existing SPF TXT record on the host and recalculate the resulting SPF TXT record. In case several sources specify the same rule with a different policy DNS Provider SHOULD apply the least restrictive one as a result. <tt>soft failure</tt> SHOULD be preferred over <tt>hard failure</tt>, <tt>neutral</tt> SHOULD be preferred over <tt>soft failure</tt>.</t>

<t anchor="_c5734b42-8db1-9162-e77e-d2ea7d5517d0">DNS Provider SHOULD also allow the end user to modify the SPF record after merging.</t>

<t anchor="_2314391e-0f1d-b38d-dc5d-7c23dc52ff95">Due to merging step in between, the resulting SPF TXT records are considered non-essential (see: <xref target="non-essential-record"></xref>). That means the user may decide to override the final calculated value or remove the whole SPF record. This action MUST NOT lead to removal of any related templates in conflict detection and template integrity routines if implemented by the DNS Provider.</t>

<t anchor="_46588dcb-aa2d-4204-4e21-4e34a6cce4b1">If the existing TXT record makes the merging operation not possible, the DNS Provider MUST handle this situation the same way as a conflict and either let the end-user resolve it in the UX (both in Synchronous and Asynchronous flow) or return the conflict as an error in the Asynchronous flow unless the <tt>force=true</tt> parameter is used, effectively removing the existing record.</t>

<t anchor="_fafc4b51-c4a6-8a7d-5f5b-aabe669b6c17">Service Providers MUST NOT check content of TXT SPF record for an exact match, as it might be strongly influenced by the DNS Provider merging strategy and user actions.</t>

<t anchor="_cea18768-740a-51c8-cf2a-ea1c128e019c">See <xref target="example-spf-merge"></xref>.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="_6e073279-a067-be86-2dda-06112f1d79d3"><name>Alternatives</name>

<t anchor="_ef5a71fc-e1ac-3a1f-9890-9908a90ec12c">Some DNS Providers MAY decide not to support the SPFM record. The following alternative solution would allow general interoperability of the templates for those providers: onboard the templates with SPFM record in variable-compatible form using a regular TXT record with content <tt>"v=spf1 %spfRules% ~all"</tt>, using property <tt>essential=OnApply</tt> set to avoid removal of the whole template by a conflict.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="repository-and-integrity"><name>Public Template Repository</name>

<section anchor="_432563de-66bf-76b5-2756-13197f6486b7"><name>General information</name>

<t anchor="_f3750d37-dcfa-d6fe-be93-6b82c375b414">The Public Template Repository is an open accessible location where Service Providers MAY publish their Service Templates in the format specified in this specification. DNS Providers MAY support all of the published templates, just a subset or none of them according to own onboarding policies (see also:  <xref target="onboarding-considerations"></xref>).</t>

<t anchor="_1a4e2be3-175c-9d0f-723b-4223930b8b3e">The template format is intended largely for documentation and communication between the DNS Providers and Service Providers, and there are no codified endpoints for creation or modification of these objects. Instead, Domain Connect references a template by ID.</t>

<t anchor="_96799c0d-a971-1261-49e1-48cdb11b0efc">As such, DNS Providers may or may not use templates in this format in their internal implementations. By defining a standard template format, it is believed it will make it easier for Service Providers to share their configuration across DNS Providers.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="_1b753188-51ec-5b2b-7ffb-db9ef46826c2"><name>Repository Location</name>

<t anchor="_7355457e-2cbc-3ae5-4dcf-f921b485d149">The  repository of the templates is maintained under <eref target="https://github.com/Domain-Connect/templates"></eref>.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="repository-file-names-requirements"><name>File naming requirements</name>

<t anchor="_0af54312-906f-6631-fb23-315cae8bc786">The file names in this repository MUST be all lower case, including the <tt>providerId</tt> and <tt>serviceId</tt>. As a result, while the <tt>providerId</tt> and <tt>serviceId can be mixed case, all `providerIds</tt> and <tt>serviceIds</tt> in this repository MUST be unique when lower case.</t>

<t anchor="_0ed3a522-85b6-223c-58eb-34ee798dc144">Templates MUST be named according the following pattern: <tt>{providerId}.{serviceId}.json</tt></t>

<sourcecode anchor="_563ac5e3-0d50-5c20-c1ba-2e3f7216d57e"><![CDATA[providerId: example.com
serviceId: WebsiteBuilder

Template file name: example.com.websitebuilder.json]]></sourcecode>

</section>

<section anchor="_6e9af21a-fc06-ea59-4db5-6927fed2d196"><name>Template Integrity</name>

<t anchor="_a62d121f-e1fd-7efc-e20e-41477a048933">Implementers are responsible for data integrity and MUST use the record type field to validate that variable input meets the criteria for each different data type.</t>

<t anchor="_a9fc90ee-4727-f265-e412-28243f89c98f">Hard-coded host names are the responsibility of the DNS Provider to protect. That is, DNS Providers MUST ensure that host names do not interfere with known values (such as <tt>m.</tt> or <tt>www.</tt> or <tt>mail.</tt>) or internal names that provide critical functionality that is outside the scope of this specification.</t>
</section>
</section>
</section>
    <section anchor="_befcabc9-c6c6-fd2b-6173-7de9cdcf46da"><name>General considerations</name>

<section anchor="onboarding-considerations"><name>Onboarding</name>

<t anchor="_66580ace-7449-d4ee-897c-ddf0a561169c">This specification is an open standard that describes the protocol, messages and formats used to enable Domain Connect between a Service Provider and a DNS Provider.</t>

<t anchor="_73dda0f0-b178-ba2f-926a-85f15e10077b">Any Service Provider is free to define and publish a template. However, the terms and conditions for a DNS Provider onboarding a Service Provider template is beyond the scope of this document. A DNS Provider can be selective in what templates they support, can require a contractual relationship, or even charge a fee for onboarding.</t>

<t anchor="_94d973ef-19a0-a890-9e8e-77dd0601d483">One way a Service Provider can be selective in which DNS Providers they accept is to implement a whitelist of <tt>providerIds</tt>. A Service Provider who chooses to whitelist MUST use <tt>providerId</tt> to distinguish between unique DNS Providers. The DNS Provider's <tt>providerId</tt> would typically be a domain name.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="_7964e7b3-78ae-a2bd-c62e-56a84c23de9a"><name>Case Sensitivity</name>

<t anchor="_0416cfbf-4907-bd4f-a4ac-343aa0e6a764">All values are case sensitive. This includes variable names, values, parameters and objects returned.</t>

<t anchor="_32ded516-44e9-e4d2-c14b-fea1e45698e0">One exception is the domain/host name. This is because a fully qualified domain name is case insensitive.</t>

<t anchor="_606b06be-d5db-7163-02b6-925f151cdc5a">The values for providerId/serviceId in the template and passed through URIs in the path or query string are case sensitive. Different rules apply to the file naming in the <xref target="repository-file-names-requirements">Public Template Repository</xref>.</t>
</section>
</section>
    <section anchor="_73468c0d-3a32-2a2e-9d62-2a4ff9a66eb5"><name>Extensions/Exclusions</name>

<section anchor="_713de860-fb30-6d54-ba79-7b99fbca2b61"><name>General information</name>

<t anchor="_8e9f3bae-7916-ce15-6408-f5c58d52d772">Additional record types and/or extensions to records in the template can be implemented on a per DNS Provider basis. However, care should be taken when defining extensions so as to not conflict with other protocols and standards. Certain record names are reserved for use in DNS for protocols like DNSSEC (DNSKEY, RRSIG) <xref target="RFC9364" section="" relative=""></xref> at the registry level.</t>

<t anchor="_14253881-0bda-98a8-fe88-22725581e4e7">Defining these OPTIONAL extensions in an open manner as part of this specification is done to provide consistency. The following are the initial OPTIONAL extensions a DNS Provider/Service Provider may support.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="_90ae47ea-976f-ade5-ca20-9fff8d978ddb"><name>APEXCNAME</name>

<t anchor="_9cf73af5-ed6c-f739-3ccb-2bae3786d904">Some Service Providers desire the behavior of a CNAME record, but in the apex record. This would allow for an A Record at the root of the domain but dynamically determined at runtime.</t>

<t anchor="_29c6fdfb-a6ef-e10f-c864-5e69db73a087">The recommended record type for DNS Providers that wish to support this is an APEXCNAME record. Additional fields included with this record would include pointsTo and TTL.</t>

<t anchor="_2055aa15-d61a-194b-34cc-81e6d839edf4">Defining a standard for such functionality in DNS is beyond the scope of this specification. But for DNS Providers that support this functionality, using the same record type name across DNS Providers allows template reuse.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="_e65fc1a9-43f2-4f2c-28d4-4b2e4f94b26a"><name>Redirection</name>

<t anchor="_d75c25aa-8944-281e-c6a2-11d57028b0b3">Some Service Providers desire a redirection service associated with the A Record. A typical example is a service that requires a redirect of the domain (e.g. example.com) to the www variant (www.example.com). The www would often contain a CNAME.</t>

<t anchor="_b1a730c3-168f-caeb-bab9-e530701349b8">Since implementation of a redirection service is typically simple, it is recommended that Service Providers implement redirection on their own. But for DNS Providers that have a redirection service, supporting simple templates with this functionality may be desired.</t>

<t anchor="_42c0f9c7-6f7a-8adb-cf7f-764a4caf0a1b">While technically not a "record" in DNS, when supporting this OPTIONAL functionality it is recommended that this SHOULD be implemented using two new record types.</t>

<t anchor="_83f22715-5842-3496-e96c-3def041aaa2b">REDIR301 and REDIR302 would implement 301 and 302 redirects respectively. Associated with this record would be a single field called the "target", containing the target url of the redirect.</t>

<t anchor="_66a76a5c-1fd1-1457-bfbb-294ff96cb402">Please note, that setting up an HTTP redirect typically involves setting up a webserver and configuring A and AAAA records pointing to this webserver accordingly. The template may or may not explicitly define those records, as the orchestration and the values would we controlled by the DNS provider, not the Service Provider. The DNS Provider SHOULD however consider those records during the conflict resolution in order to give transparency of the changes to the user.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="_718122cd-10c8-5127-e3bf-46d2706d855d"><name>Nameservers</name>

<t anchor="_2f56a572-3b42-edcb-f59c-be34d6ff1bd6">Several Service Providers have asked for functionality supporting an update to the nameserver records at the registry associated with the domain.</t>

<t anchor="_35a4555f-c075-fa5e-8ae5-b1f1d2a5cb9d">When implementing this functionality a template defined at DNS Provider would need to define a set of NS records, typically a minimum of 2 and a maximum depending on the number supported by the registrar system of the DNS Provider, likely with <tt>groupIds</tt> to allow for optionality of those additional nameservers. Each NS entry would then contain a <tt>data</tt> field with desired host names or variables to allow for dynamic setup.</t>

<t anchor="_9e2424b0-c58a-5f40-5701-22a49f4ee7cd">It will be noted that a nameserver update would require that the entity implementing DNS Provider side of the protocol is the Registrar. This is not always the case.</t>

<t anchor="_62aa2793-61a4-b55b-61e3-3de3dbce5844">Additional care would have to be taken by the DNS Provider informing the user about the change happening and the impact of the change.</t>

<t anchor="_526b4ec1-864f-b204-b621-876e0b9f018e">This functionality is again deemed as OPTIONAL and up to the DNS Provider to determine if they will support this.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="_47370a77-5e32-b080-1302-a12d2658c13e"><name>DS (DNSSEC)</name>

<t anchor="_5e2afb1d-46f6-f272-36c4-177801597286">Requests have been made to allow for updates to the DS record for DNSSEC. This record is required at the registry to enable DNSSEC, but can only be written by the registrar.</t>

<t anchor="_fc6efd81-356a-579e-4ff2-adbcd2199e11">For DNS Providers that support this record, the record type would be DS. Values will be keyTag, algorithm, digestType, and digest.</t>

<t anchor="_b3d6d2b5-ce36-18d7-d078-06213f0ba25e">Again it should be noted that a DS update would require that the entity implementing DNS Provider side of the protocol is the registrar, and is again deemed as OPTIONAL and up to the DNS Provider to determine if they will support.</t>
</section>
</section>
    <section anchor="iana"><name>IANA Considerations</name>

<t anchor="_62c9a2e7-9390-8c78-1997-774e28e3d332">Per <xref target="RFC8552" section="" relative=""></xref>, please add the following entry to the "Underscored and Globally Scoped DNS Node Names" registry:</t>

<table anchor="_ff14f8c7-e119-b8c8-1853-30cacf6a7275"><name>IANA Registration for _domainconnect</name><thead><tr><th align="left">RR Type</th><th align="left">_NODE NAME</th><th align="left">Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">TXT</td><td align="left">_domainconnect</td><td align="left">This document.</td></tr></tbody></table>
</section>
    <section anchor="_23c08eba-9535-0405-cf44-3053f463f1b3" numbered="false" removeInRFC="true" toc="include"><name>Implementation Status</name>

<section anchor="_a17dd78a-20ba-ea96-c489-042d3b3cbe72" numbered="false" toc="exclude"><name>DNS Providers</name>

<section anchor="_65b664c5-3add-d3b5-b219-90487e568398" numbered="false" toc="exclude"><name>Open Source</name>

<ul anchor="_7d03fdbd-6040-a6e1-0a01-19918aee25bb"><li>Server library (Python):<eref target="https://github.com/Domain-Connect/DomainConnectApplyZone"></eref></li>
</ul>
</section>

<section anchor="_5fe41413-f9b6-d114-20dc-3abc9572b88f" numbered="false" toc="exclude"><name>Priopriatery implementations</name>

<ul anchor="_1846ed1e-991d-42f0-8c76-e8304606b64f"><li>~20 providers, incl. GoDaddy, IONOS, Cloudflare, Squarespace Domains (former Google), Wordpress.com or Plesk</li>
<li>35% of the .com zone (May'24)</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="_41d607fd-b283-5f78-6015-37c0a8bbf06b" numbered="false" toc="exclude"><name>Service Providers</name>

<section anchor="_3a3467ee-153c-94ef-ab72-ea5a0143306b" numbered="false" toc="exclude"><name>Open Source</name>

<ul anchor="_aea7010d-f27e-9bf1-4b7b-0bcd0262eec0"><li>Example service: <eref target="https://exampleservice.domainconnect.org/"></eref><eref target="https://github.com/Domain-Connect/exampleservice"></eref></li>
<li>Client library (Python):<eref target="https://github.com/Domain-Connect/domainconnect_python"></eref></li>
</ul>
</section>

<section anchor="_82df7701-f3c1-c6cc-b5a0-9c6992169751" numbered="false" toc="exclude"><name>Priopriatery implementations</name>

<ul anchor="_bf5011d1-6391-4737-7fef-023cf3b53c5a"><li>300 templates from over 120 providers, incl. O365, Google Workspace, Apple Cloud+, Weebly, Squarespace...<eref target="https://github.com/Domain-Connect/Templates"></eref></li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
</section>
    <section anchor="_ffdf0cd3-e0e4-8a45-53dc-364be5f5b5be" numbered="false" removeInRFC="true" toc="include"><name>Change History</name>

<section anchor="_2973a14d-a659-c946-d43c-7b5c47c2a088" numbered="false" toc="exclude"><name>Change from -01 to -02</name>

<ul anchor="_d9b3f85c-2a0c-efe3-30e1-01327eea3a8b"><li>Draft refresh from expire.  No content changes.</li>
</ul>
</section>

<section anchor="_1dd480a2-440c-24a6-2838-7c998777b9d1" numbered="false" toc="exclude"><name>Change from -00 to -01</name>

<ul anchor="_e457ea59-8c50-02fe-caad-cba191131b88"><li>Changed term Root Domain to Zone Apex to align with <xref target="RFC8499" section="" relative=""></xref>.</li>
<li>Removed example provider names from Service Providers and DNS Providers teminology</li>
<li>Added Use Cases</li>
<li>Added Trust Model</li>
<li>Added sequence diagrams for synchronous and asynchronous flows instead of UX mocks</li>
<li>Reviewed use of normative language</li>
<li>Cleaned up usage of terminology</li>
<li>Variable substitution description updated</li>
<li>All URLs are now normatively defined with URI templates</li>
</ul>
</section>

<section anchor="_6b64490f-bbf3-7745-29d5-58574222ed31" numbered="false" toc="exclude"><name>Change from draft-kowalik-regext-domainconnect-00 to draft-kowalik-domainconnect-00</name>

<ul anchor="_89d5cd4a-1d0d-c9a1-d633-efd7fe50b794"><li>Added possibility to specify any DNS record type in a generic manner.</li>
<li>Added possibility to define variables for numeric fields.</li>
<li>Added IANA registration for _domainconnect record as per <xref target="RFC8552" section="" relative=""></xref></li>
</ul>
</section>

<section anchor="_9dc102df-4f45-d8a8-8525-d1d963691301" numbered="false" toc="exclude"><name>Change from draft-carney-regext-domainconnect-03 to draft-kowalik-regext-domainconnect-00</name>

<ul anchor="_4d27d511-d44e-f4d4-0b99-58c8e13e7e39"><li>Version synchronized with 2.2 version rev. 66 of the public Domain Connect specification.</li>
</ul>
</section>

<section anchor="_fa50be0d-d43e-30ce-8edc-9c15c5c91886" numbered="false" toc="exclude"><name>Change from -02 to -03</name>

<ul anchor="_47fd5501-0992-a122-3494-3e022b4fe5a5"><li>Added width/height JSON values returned by DNS Provider Discovery.</li>
<li>Corrected text of GET method for getting the authorization token.</li>
<li>Added clarifying text to Group ID description parameter of the apply template POST method.  Quite a few minor edits and clarifications that were found during implementation, especially in the Implementation Considerations section.</li>
</ul>
</section>

<section anchor="_5c45df0e-21f7-698a-b69e-856bb7fd4f9f" numbered="false" toc="exclude"><name>Change from -01 to -02</name>

<ul anchor="_1da8ee6f-5a0a-2024-d979-1f66d4aed9d7"><li>Added new GET method for Service Providers to determine if the DNS Provider supports a specific template.  Some other minor edits for clarification.</li>
</ul>
</section>

<section anchor="_939446fb-9c0b-a91d-baad-bb542f0cf5f7" numbered="false" toc="exclude"><name>Change from draft-carney-regext-domainconnect-00 to -01</name>

<ul anchor="_b0b8f5af-dab9-1c15-a31b-8fbc505e4107"><li>Minor edits and clarifications found during implementation.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references anchor="_774b7859-f1eb-fe24-e8a0-78143bfe79b7">
      <name>Normative References</name>
      <reference target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc1035" anchor="RFC1035"><front> <title>Domain names - implementation and specification</title> <author fullname="P. Mockapetris" asciiFullname="P. Mockapetris"></author> <date month="November" year="1987"></date> <keyword>DOMAIN</keyword><keyword>DNS</keyword> <abstract>  <t anchor="_aa3804f6-cf5f-52d9-e4c5-bc354524dec1">This RFC is the revised specification of the protocol and format used in the implementation of the Domain Name System. It obsoletes RFC-883. This memo documents the details of the domain name client - server communication.</t></abstract> </front> <seriesInfo name="STD" value="13"></seriesInfo> <seriesInfo value="10.17487/RFC1035" name="DOI"></seriesInfo> <seriesInfo value="13" name="BCP"></seriesInfo> <seriesInfo value="1035" name="RFC"></seriesInfo></reference>
      <reference target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2119" anchor="RFC2119"><stream>IETF</stream> <front> <title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title> <author fullname="S. Bradner" asciiFullname="S. Bradner"></author> <date month="March" year="1997"></date> <keyword>Standards</keyword><keyword>Track</keyword><keyword>Documents</keyword> <abstract>  <t anchor="_8a4ab7df-b577-b6f5-5ec6-da65b529baf2">In many standards track documents several words are used to signify the requirements in the specification. These words are often capitalized. This document defines these words as they should be interpreted in IETF documents. This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t></abstract> </front> <seriesInfo value="10.17487/RFC2119" name="DOI"></seriesInfo> <seriesInfo value="14" name="BCP"></seriesInfo> <seriesInfo value="2119" name="RFC"></seriesInfo></reference>
      <reference target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8174" anchor="RFC8174"><stream>IETF</stream> <front> <title>Ambiguity of Uppercase vs Lowercase in RFC 2119 Key Words</title> <author fullname="B. Leiba" asciiFullname="B. Leiba"></author> <date month="May" year="2017"></date> <abstract>  <t anchor="_889e8892-f7ca-db90-bdb9-f5d3a3dc2107">RFC 2119 specifies common key words that may be used in protocol specifications. This document aims to reduce the ambiguity by clarifying that only UPPERCASE usage of the key words have the defined special meanings.</t></abstract> </front> <seriesInfo value="10.17487/RFC8174" name="DOI"></seriesInfo> <seriesInfo value="14" name="BCP"></seriesInfo> <seriesInfo value="8174" name="RFC"></seriesInfo></reference>
      <reference target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7208" anchor="RFC7208"><stream>IETF</stream> <front> <title>Sender Policy Framework (SPF) for Authorizing Use of Domains in Email, Version 1</title> <author fullname="S. Kitterman" asciiFullname="S. Kitterman"></author> <date month="April" year="2014"></date> <keyword>spoofing</keyword><keyword>spf</keyword><keyword>anti-forgery</keyword><keyword>authentication</keyword> <abstract>  <t anchor="_b417a9c6-f2a5-60e7-056d-ebd903481b16">Email on the Internet can be forged in a number of ways. In particular, existing protocols place no restriction on what a sending host can use as the "MAIL FROM" of a message or the domain given on the SMTP HELO/EHLO commands. This document describes version 1 of the Sender Policy Framework (SPF) protocol, whereby ADministrative Management Domains (ADMDs) can explicitly authorize the hosts that are allowed to use their domain names, and a receiving host can check such authorization.</t>  <t anchor="_090af402-c5b5-cf8f-24cf-da11a6452bcf">This document obsoletes RFC 4408.</t></abstract> </front> <seriesInfo value="10.17487/RFC7208" name="DOI"></seriesInfo> <seriesInfo value="7208" name="RFC"></seriesInfo></reference>
      <reference target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6749" anchor="RFC6749"><stream>IETF</stream> <front> <title>The OAuth 2.0 Authorization Framework</title> <author fullname="D. Hardt" asciiFullname="D. Hardt"></author> <date month="October" year="2012"></date> <keyword>Client</keyword><keyword>Resource Owner</keyword><keyword>Authorization Server</keyword><keyword>Resource Server</keyword><keyword>Token Endpoint</keyword><keyword>Authorization Endpoint</keyword><keyword>Authorization Request</keyword><keyword>Authorization Grant</keyword><keyword>Protected Resource</keyword><keyword>Access Token</keyword><keyword>RefreshToken</keyword><keyword>Authorization Code</keyword><keyword>Implicit Grant</keyword><keyword>Client Identifier</keyword><keyword>Access Token Scope</keyword><keyword>Delegation</keyword> <abstract>  <t anchor="_7a23b988-115b-b787-dc20-23e7edd23020">The OAuth 2.0 authorization framework enables a third-party application to obtain limited access to an HTTP service, either on behalf of a resource owner by orchestrating an approval interaction between the resource owner and the HTTP service, or by allowing the third-party application to obtain access on its own behalf. This specification replaces and obsoletes the OAuth 1.0 protocol described in RFC 5849. [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract> </front> <seriesInfo value="10.17487/RFC6749" name="DOI"></seriesInfo> <seriesInfo value="6749" name="RFC"></seriesInfo></reference>
      <reference target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc3597" anchor="RFC3597"><stream>IETF</stream> <front> <title>Handling of Unknown DNS Resource Record (RR) Types</title> <author fullname="A. Gustafsson" asciiFullname="A. Gustafsson"></author> <date month="September" year="2003"></date> <keyword>DNS</keyword><keyword>domain name system</keyword><keyword>name server software</keyword><keyword>compression</keyword><keyword>transparency</keyword><keyword>RR</keyword><keyword>Resource Record</keyword> <abstract>  <t anchor="_f3c2445f-c7b2-037a-1250-a2ed89bcf284">Extending the Domain Name System (DNS) with new Resource Record (RR) types currently requires changes to name server software. This document specifies the changes necessary to allow future DNS implementations to handle new RR types transparently. [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract> </front> <seriesInfo value="10.17487/RFC3597" name="DOI"></seriesInfo> <seriesInfo value="3597" name="RFC"></seriesInfo></reference>
      <reference target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8552" anchor="RFC8552"><stream>IETF</stream> <front> <title>Scoped Interpretation of DNS Resource Records through "Underscored" Naming of Attribute Leaves</title> <author fullname="D. Crocker" asciiFullname="D. Crocker"></author> <date month="March" year="2019"></date> <keyword>DNS</keyword><keyword>Domain Name System</keyword> <abstract>  <t anchor="_7e11052a-74e4-ef41-7453-11d4f48f39bd">Formally, any DNS Resource Record (RR) may occur under any domain name. However, some services use an operational convention for defining specific interpretations of an RRset by locating the records in a DNS branch under the parent domain to which the RRset actually applies. The top of this subordinate branch is defined by a naming convention that uses a reserved node name, which begins with the underscore character (e.g., "_name"). The underscored naming construct defines a semantic scope for DNS record types that are associated with the parent domain above the underscored branch. This specification explores the nature of this DNS usage and defines the "Underscored and Globally Scoped DNS Node Names" registry with IANA. The purpose of this registry is to avoid collisions resulting from the use of the same underscored name for different services.</t></abstract> </front> <seriesInfo value="10.17487/RFC8552" name="DOI"></seriesInfo> <seriesInfo value="222" name="BCP"></seriesInfo> <seriesInfo value="8552" name="RFC"></seriesInfo></reference>
      <reference target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc3986" anchor="RFC3986"><stream>IETF</stream> <front> <title>Uniform Resource Identifier (URI): Generic Syntax</title> <author fullname="T. Berners-Lee" asciiFullname="T. Berners-Lee"></author> <author fullname="R. Fielding" asciiFullname="R. Fielding"></author> <author fullname="L. Masinter" asciiFullname="L. Masinter"></author> <date month="January" year="2005"></date> <keyword>Internet protocol</keyword><keyword>IP</keyword><keyword>uniform resource identifier</keyword><keyword>URI</keyword><keyword>www</keyword><keyword>world wide web</keyword> <abstract>  <t anchor="_f4732bd0-81d1-4fc0-db7d-369cacdf3965">A Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) is a compact sequence of characters that identifies an abstract or physical resource. This specification defines the generic URI syntax and a process for resolving URI references that might be in relative form, along with guidelines and security considerations for the use of URIs on the Internet. The URI syntax defines a grammar that is a superset of all valid URIs, allowing an implementation to parse the common components of a URI reference without knowing the scheme-specific requirements of every possible identifier. This specification does not define a generative grammar for URIs; that task is performed by the individual specifications of each URI scheme. [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract> </front> <seriesInfo name="STD" value="66"></seriesInfo> <seriesInfo value="10.17487/RFC3986" name="DOI"></seriesInfo> <seriesInfo value="66" name="BCP"></seriesInfo> <seriesInfo value="3986" name="RFC"></seriesInfo></reference>
      <reference target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7518" anchor="RFC7518"><stream>IETF</stream> <front> <title>JSON Web Algorithms (JWA)</title> <author fullname="M. Jones" asciiFullname="M. Jones"></author> <date month="May" year="2015"></date> <abstract>  <t anchor="_5449fd72-4203-136e-f859-da801fc62246">This specification registers cryptographic algorithms and identifiers to be used with the JSON Web Signature (JWS), JSON Web Encryption (JWE), and JSON Web Key (JWK) specifications. It defines several IANA registries for these identifiers.</t></abstract> </front> <seriesInfo value="10.17487/RFC7518" name="DOI"></seriesInfo> <seriesInfo value="7518" name="RFC"></seriesInfo></reference>
      <reference target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6570" anchor="RFC6570"><stream>IETF</stream> <front> <title>URI Template</title> <author fullname="J. Gregorio" asciiFullname="J. Gregorio"></author> <author fullname="R. Fielding" asciiFullname="R. Fielding"></author> <author fullname="M. Hadley" asciiFullname="M. Hadley"></author> <author fullname="M. Nottingham" asciiFullname="M. Nottingham"></author> <author fullname="D. Orchard" asciiFullname="D. Orchard"></author> <date month="March" year="2012"></date> <keyword>template</keyword><keyword>Uniform Resource Identifier</keyword><keyword>URI</keyword><keyword>URI Template</keyword><keyword>Internationalized Resource Identifier</keyword><keyword>IRI</keyword><keyword>IRI Template</keyword> <abstract>  <t anchor="_4fb9c0b6-d969-01a1-cd6e-10483cead5d9">A URI Template is a compact sequence of characters for describing a range of Uniform Resource Identifiers through variable expansion. This specification defines the URI Template syntax and the process for expanding a URI Template into a URI reference, along with guidelines for the use of URI Templates on the Internet. [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract> </front> <seriesInfo value="10.17487/RFC6570" name="DOI"></seriesInfo> <seriesInfo value="6570" name="RFC"></seriesInfo></reference>
      <reference target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5234" anchor="RFC5234"><stream>IETF</stream> <front> <title>Augmented BNF for Syntax Specifications: ABNF</title> <author fullname="P. Overell" asciiFullname="P. Overell"></author> <author fullname="D. Crocker" asciiFullname="D. Crocker"></author> <date month="January" year="2008"></date> <keyword>ABNF</keyword><keyword>backus-naur form</keyword><keyword>augmented backus-naur form</keyword><keyword>rule definitions</keyword><keyword>encoding</keyword><keyword>core lexical analyzer</keyword> <abstract>  <t anchor="_82641f5b-cb79-2f24-f111-fcd2e7030e5d">Internet technical specifications often need to define a formal syntax. Over the years, a modified version of Backus-Naur Form (BNF), called Augmented BNF (ABNF), has been popular among many Internet specifications. The current specification documents ABNF. It balances compactness and simplicity with reasonable representational power. The differences between standard BNF and ABNF involve naming rules, repetition, alternatives, order-independence, and value ranges. This specification also supplies additional rule definitions and encoding for a core lexical analyzer of the type common to several Internet specifications. [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract> </front> <seriesInfo name="STD" value="68"></seriesInfo> <seriesInfo value="10.17487/RFC5234" name="DOI"></seriesInfo> <seriesInfo value="68" name="BCP"></seriesInfo> <seriesInfo value="5234" name="RFC"></seriesInfo></reference>
    </references>
    <references anchor="_fd5a71b3-af69-4a59-5cfe-2ee74c9acb1b">
      <name>Informative References</name>
      <reference target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc9364" anchor="RFC9364"><stream>IETF</stream> <front> <title>DNS Security Extensions (DNSSEC)</title> <author fullname="P. Hoffman" asciiFullname="P. Hoffman"></author> <date month="February" year="2023"></date> <keyword>DNSSEC</keyword><keyword>DNS Security Extensions</keyword><keyword>DNS</keyword> <abstract>  <t anchor="_83b7fddf-54b1-b02f-16e6-0b24262cb108">This document describes the DNS Security Extensions (commonly called "DNSSEC") that are specified in RFCs 4033, 4034, and 4035, as well as a handful of others. One purpose is to introduce all of the RFCs in one place so that the reader can understand the many aspects of DNSSEC. This document does not update any of those RFCs. A second purpose is to state that using DNSSEC for origin authentication of DNS data is the best current practice. A third purpose is to provide a single reference for other documents that want to refer to DNSSEC.</t></abstract> </front> <seriesInfo value="10.17487/RFC9364" name="DOI"></seriesInfo> <seriesInfo value="237" name="BCP"></seriesInfo> <seriesInfo value="9364" name="RFC"></seriesInfo></reference>
      <reference target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8499" anchor="RFC8499"><stream>IETF</stream> <front> <title>DNS Terminology</title> <author fullname="P. Hoffman" asciiFullname="P. Hoffman"></author> <author fullname="A. Sullivan" asciiFullname="A. Sullivan"></author> <author fullname="K. Fujiwara" asciiFullname="K. Fujiwara"></author> <date month="January" year="2019"></date> <keyword>vocabulary</keyword><keyword>domain name system</keyword> <abstract>  <t anchor="_1f5d3ff8-eb51-5b33-aa17-a4d14c99fe43">The Domain Name System (DNS) is defined in literally dozens of different RFCs. The terminology used by implementers and developers of DNS protocols, and by operators of DNS systems, has sometimes changed in the decades since the DNS was first defined. This document gives current definitions for many of the terms used in the DNS in a single document.</t>  <t anchor="_955272cc-ccf5-7988-87c6-66a9c1b50330">This document obsoletes RFC 7719 and updates RFC 2308.</t></abstract> </front> <seriesInfo value="10.17487/RFC8499" name="DOI"></seriesInfo> <seriesInfo value="8499" name="RFC"></seriesInfo></reference>
      <reference target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7591" anchor="RFC7591"><stream>IETF</stream> <front> <title>OAuth 2.0 Dynamic Client Registration Protocol</title> <author fullname="M. Jones" asciiFullname="M. Jones"></author> <author fullname="J. Bradley" asciiFullname="J. Bradley"></author> <author fullname="M. Machulak" asciiFullname="M. Machulak"></author> <author fullname="P. Hunt" asciiFullname="P. Hunt"></author> <author fullname="J. Richer" asciiFullname="J. Richer"></author> <date month="July" year="2015"></date> <keyword>OpenID Connect Dynamic Client Registration</keyword><keyword>OpenID Connect</keyword><keyword>oidc</keyword><keyword>openid</keyword><keyword>user managed access</keyword><keyword>uma</keyword><keyword>Dynamic Registration</keyword><keyword>Dynamic Client Registration</keyword> <abstract>  <t anchor="_8860866d-13c4-68f0-b90a-dae250048305">This specification defines mechanisms for dynamically registering OAuth 2.0 clients with authorization servers. Registration requests send a set of desired client metadata values to the authorization server. The resulting registration responses return a client identifier to use at the authorization server and the client metadata values registered for the client. The client can then use this registration information to communicate with the authorization server using the OAuth 2.0 protocol. This specification also defines a set of common client metadata fields and values for clients to use during registration.</t></abstract> </front> <seriesInfo value="10.17487/RFC7591" name="DOI"></seriesInfo> <seriesInfo value="7591" name="RFC"></seriesInfo></reference>
    </references>
    <section anchor="_66f71993-fd8b-f9f9-2da5-cfa834e6cc84"><name>Examples</name>

<section anchor="_1e0ac6d1-639b-fed3-f5f4-bea82b81f3ef"><name>Example Template</name>

<sourcecode anchor="_69699bee-2535-9f96-c1b1-c414e3b03cca" type="json"><![CDATA[{
    "providerId": "example.com",
    "providerName": "Example Web Hosting",
    "serviceId": "hosting",
    "serviceName": "Wordpress by example.com",
    "version": 1,
    "logoUrl": "https://www.example.com/images/billthecat.jpg",
    "description": "This connects your domain to our web hosting",
    "records": [
        {
            "type": "A",
            "groupId": "service",
            "host": "www",
            "pointsTo": "%var1%",
            "ttl": 600
        },
        {
            "type": "A",
            "groupId": "service",
            "host": "m",
            "pointsTo": "%var2%",
            "ttl": 600
        },
        {
            "type": "CNAME",
            "groupId": "service",
            "host": "webmail",
            "pointsTo": "%var3%",
            "ttl": 600
        },
        {
            "type": "TXT",
            "groupId": "verification",
            "host": "example",
            "ttl": 600,
            "data": "%var4%"
        }
    ]
}]]></sourcecode>

</section>

<section anchor="_7aef545b-ba44-3cf9-34fa-6a1f67b99775"><name>Example Records: Single static host record</name>

<t anchor="_8a1cd115-8ed5-69aa-4cd1-395b528b20d7">Consider a template for setting a single host record. The records section of the template would have a single record of type "A" and could have a value of:</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_6320ad16-946e-0563-e003-17438fb13a24" type="json"><![CDATA[[{
    "type": "A",
    "host": "www",
    "pointsTo": "192.0.2.1",
    "ttl": 600
}]]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_fb82714c-f097-6841-ea23-0e36e5fbc65d">This would have no variable substitution and the application of this template to a domain would simply set the host name "www" to the IP address "192.0.2.1"</t>
</section>

<section anchor="_e60cc03e-eef3-36d7-5c8c-8079eea93a0a"><name>Example Records: Single variable host record for A</name>

<t anchor="_129d4971-39c4-eb7d-d316-3aa4fa8b4ac2">In the case of a template for setting a single host record from a variable, the template would have a single record of type "A" and could have a value of:</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_60f2004a-fc9b-632b-c199-199fdef053da" type="json"><![CDATA[[{
    "type": "A",
    "host": "@",
    "pointsTo": "198.51.100.%srv%",
    "ttl": 600
}]]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_a6e777f6-47cb-b34d-aaa0-f149bc8e9ba3">A query string with a key/value pair of</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_041bac04-0760-9a2d-de0b-1093e44a86db"><![CDATA[srv=2]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_aa9c3f63-3a57-4d08-0cdf-37d12f07b06c">would cause the application of this template to a domain to set the host name for the apex A record to the IP address "198.51.100.2" with a TTL of 600</t>
</section>

<section anchor="_60f2d70c-cc6c-e05f-7e94-2560ad31c8ef"><name>Example Records: Unspecified record type CAA</name>

<t anchor="_c9782a55-c8ef-a117-6f64-1fbb3c9104ab">This example shows how to include a set of unspecified record types on an example of CAA records:</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_1446da49-7cfd-b40e-a2d8-e15da327870b" type="json"><![CDATA[[
    {
        "type": "CAA",
        "host": "@",
        "data": "0 issue \"ca1.example.net\"",
        "ttl": 1800
    },
    {
        "type": "CAA",
        "host": "@",
        "data": "0 issuewild \"ca2.example.\"",
        "ttl": 1800
    }
]]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_4a7bb606-9a11-7985-ceaf-688bf3e4236c">This would have no variable substitution and the application of this template to a domain would add 2 CAA records.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="_478eaa15-ab9b-8d09-af4f-0324e2f3d1ae"><name>Example: DNS Zone merging</name>

<t anchor="_4559b1e8-3fdb-177e-febc-050f2fc06d35">Consider a DNS Zone before a template application:</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_073dbaab-e649-b1e3-54fb-a6a6f336f025"><![CDATA[$ORIGIN example.com.

@ 3600 IN SOA ns11.example.net. support.example.net. 2017050817 7200
1800 1209600 3600
@ 3600 IN NS ns11.example.net.
@ 3600 IN NS ns12.example.net.
@ 3600 IN A 192.0.2.1
@ 3600 IN A 192.0.2.2
@ 3600 IN AAAA 2001:db8:1234:0000:0000:0000:0000:0000
@ 3600 IN AAAA 2001:db8:1234:0000:0000:0000:0000:0001
@ 3600 IN MX 10 mx1.example.net.
@ 3600 IN MX 10 mx2.example.net.
@ 3600 IN TXT "v=spf1 a include:spf.example.org ~all"
www 3600 IN CNAME other.host.example.]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_36edeecd-7d04-d3d8-e995-a6b9aeeaeb54">Now application of the following template:</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_c951e767-823d-6a12-8d9e-a8f30cda6c9c" type="json"><![CDATA[[
    {
        "type":"A",
        "host":"@",
        "pointsTo":"203.0.113.2",
        "ttl":"1800"
    },
    {
        "type":"A",
        "host":"www",
        "pointsTo":"203.0.113.2",
        "ttl":"1800"
    },
    {
        "type":"SPFM",
        "host":"@",
        "spfRules":"a include:spf.hoster.example"
    }
]]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_c099ef2c-c8f4-e321-8174-574899ab3f76">The following DNS Zone would be generated after the template is applied:</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_46ab3005-f346-5843-e226-27c0acc170b1"><![CDATA[$ORIGIN example.com.

@ 3600 IN SOA ns11.example.net. support.example.net. 2017050920 7200
1800 1209600 3600
@ 3600 IN NS ns11.example.net.
@ 3600 IN NS ns12.example.net.
@ 1800 IN A 203.0.113.2
@ 3600 IN MX 10 mx1.example.net.
@ 3600 IN MX 10 mx2.example.net.
@ 1800 IN TXT "v=spf1 a include:spf.example.org include:spf.hoster.ex
ample ~all"
www 1800 IN A 203.0.113.2]]></sourcecode>

</section>

<section anchor="example-spf-merge"><name>Example: SPF Record Merging</name>

<t anchor="_4d228712-461e-93ef-a48d-c8168d1630f9">Consider a DNS Zone before a template application:</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_88a6396b-b4a1-7ab3-7647-009eb7167201"><![CDATA[$ORIGIN example.com.

@ 3600 IN SOA ns11.example.net. support.example.net. 2017050817 7200
1800 1209600 3600
@ 3600 IN NS ns11.example.net.
@ 3600 IN NS ns12.example.net.]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_f4b921be-1689-7721-a9be-f5e5bc51a503">Now application of the following template of Mail service:</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_4b0a7f2d-4219-921d-c9bb-c703ca436a8e" type="json"><![CDATA[[
    {
        "type":"MX",
        "host":"@",
        "priority": "10",
        "pointsTo":"mx1.example.net",
        "ttl":"1800"
    },
    {
        "type":"MX",
        "host":"www",
        "priority": "10",
        "pointsTo":"mx2.example.net",
        "ttl":"1800"
    },
    {
        "type":"SPFM",
        "host":"@",
        "spfRules":"a include:spf.example.net"
    }
]]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_2164ceea-eb15-1387-c549-bd0c0ef87339">Expected result in the DNS Zone</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_106d1e96-97c5-0a0f-1139-cb14c907af1e"><![CDATA[$ORIGIN example.com.

@ 3600 IN SOA ns11.example.net. support.example.net. 2017050817 7200
1800 1209600 3600
@ 3600 IN NS ns11.example.net.
@ 3600 IN NS ns12.example.net.
@ 3600 IN MX 10 mx1.example.net.
@ 3600 IN MX 10 mx2.example.net.
@ 3600 IN TXT "v=spf1 a include:spf.example.net ~all"]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_0662cc37-7e3b-9261-8066-5004809fb669">In the next step application of the following template of Newsletter service:</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_00715d3a-7849-a6d8-21ee-c57272977611" type="json"><![CDATA[[
    {
        "type":"SPFM",
        "host":"@",
        "spfRules":"include:_spf.newsletter.example"
    }
]]]></sourcecode>


<t anchor="_5ea5797d-bdcf-ef2b-b976-2ddddf692d04">Expected result in the DNS Zone</t>

<sourcecode anchor="_8c24e7c4-01c0-889e-b6b7-fc7227cab625"><![CDATA[$ORIGIN example.com.

@ 3600 IN SOA ns11.example.net. support.example.net. 2017050817 7200
1800 1209600 3600
@ 3600 IN NS ns11.example.net.
@ 3600 IN NS ns12.example.net.
@ 3600 IN MX 10 mx1.example.net.
@ 3600 IN MX 10 mx2.example.net.
@ 3600 IN TXT "v=spf1 a include:spf.example.net include:_spf.newslett
er.
example ~all"]]></sourcecode>

</section>
</section>
  </back>
</rfc>
